斯坦福大学
Stanford University.
欢迎来到 2013/2014 学年秋 CS193P 课程的第二课
Well, welcome to lecture number two of CS 193P for fall of 2013/2014 academic year.
今天最开始我们将有一些幻灯片
And today we’re going to have some slides at the beginning,
一点讲课 然后我将有一个很大的 demo
little more talking, and then I’m going to have quite a big demo that’s going to try
我希望用它来综合前两讲
and hopefully synthesize all the things I’ve been talking
我讲过的这些内容
about on the slides for the first two lectures,
也就是 我们将开始创建我们的纸牌游戏
which is that we’re going to start building our card game.
这个纸牌匹配游戏
Okay. This card matching game
将是我们头两周的基础材料 用以学习 Objective-C
is going to be our substrate for the first two weeks of learning some Objective-C,
学习 Xcode 学习 iOS 如何衔接起
learning about Xcode, learning about how iOS hooks
控制器 视图以及模型 来建立 UI
up the controller, and the view, and the model to make a UI.
记得上次 我讲了这整个 Card 类
So if you remember from last time, we did this card thing that — we did the entire card.
这个类很简单
It was a very simple class.
它有三个属性和一个方法
Got a couple of properties — three properties there — and one method.
就这么简单
And that’s pretty much it.
今天我们将继续考虑另一个类 也就是 Deck
And so today we’re going to go on and do another class, which is a deck.
表示牌堆
The deck of cards.
记住 Card 和 Deck 是通用的
And remember, that card and deck are generic;
它们并非专门针对扑克牌
they’re not specific to playing cards, right?
扑克牌是 PlayingCard 诸如梅花 A 红心 K 这些
A playing card, like the ace of clubs or the king of hearts –
something that has all that in it — that’s a playing card thing.
这里是笼统的纸牌和牌堆
These are general cards and decks.
可以是一副抽认卡
So this could be a deck of flash cards,
一副外语单词卡等等
a deck of foreign language words you’re trying to learn or whatever.
所以 我们希望这些 Deck 和 Card 类具有通用性
So we’re trying to keep these deck and card classes somewhat generic.
这是 Deck
So here’s deck.
其基础结构你们应该熟悉
It should look familiar in terms of its basic structure, right?
这里导入我们的父类框架
We’re importing our superclasses framework there,
然后在实现中导入我们的头文件
and then obviously importing our own header file in our implementation.
Deck 的接口将有这样两个基础方法
And the interface for deck is going to have these two kind of fundamental methods:
一是将纸牌加到牌堆中
One adds a card to the deck
一是随机从牌堆中抽取一张牌
and one draws a random card out of the deck.
添加纸牌到牌堆中的方法对你们而言有些新
And the add a card to the deck is a little bit new to you
因为你们会看到它有两个参数
because you can see it has two arguments.
这是你们第一次看到有两个参数的方法
This is the first method you’ve seen that has two arguments.
之前你们看到的方法要么是没有参数
So far you’ve only seen methods with no arguments or a method
要么只有一个参数 如 match
with one argument like that — match –
match 只有一个参数 或 setter 也只有一个参数
match had one argument or the setters, they also have one argument.
注意 Objective-C 中当你有多个参数时
So notice that when you have multiple arguments
它们会穿插在方法名中间
in objective C, they’re kind of interspersed with the names of the methods.
这个方法的名称是 addCard 冒号 atTop 冒号
So the name of this method, this long method is add card colon at top colon.
这是该方法的名称
That’s the name of this method.
atTop 这部分其实也是方法名的一部分
So the at top part is actually part of the name of this method.
而参数 像这里要加的纸牌 card
And the arguments, like the card that you’re going to add
和表示在牌堆上方还是下方的布尔值 atTop
and at top — which is a Boolean whether to add it at the top
of the deck or at the bottom of the deck –
这些参数穿插在方法名中间
those arguments are interspersed.
等下你们会看到 这种方法如何调用
And we’ll see how you call such a method in a moment here.
然后随机抽取一张牌的方法
And then draw a random card is like a, you know,
没有参数 会返回一个值 这方面同 getter 类似
similar to a getter in that it returns a value and it has no arguments.
但这不是 getter 因为我们没有将它作为一个属性
But this is not a getter because we didn’t make this a property.
很重要的一点是
And it’s kind of important
你可以把它弄成一个属性
to understand you could have made this a property
例如只读属性这些
like a read-only property or something that reads it,
但随机抽取一张牌做了一些事情
but since draw a random card kind of does something,
它有一个算法 一个机制
it has kind of an algorithm to it — a mechanism –
通常不要把它弄成属性
you usually wouldn’t make that a property.
让 getter 做这个可以说是滥用
It’s kind of an abuse of a getter to do that.
getter 的作用只是设置和获取一个值
A getter is really just setting and getting a value.
它可能有副作用 设置可能更新 UI
It might have side effects, like setting it might update the UI
或者获取可能确保先初始化了 诸如此类
or getting it might make sure it’s initialized first — those kind of things.
做一些事的方法
You’re not going to — something that does something
例如抽取一张牌不要弄成属性
like drawing a card is not going to be a property.
如果你想要 atTop 这样的参数可选
Now, if you want to have, like, that at top argument be optional,
Objective-C 中的唯一做法是
okay, the only way to do that in Objective-C –
显然我们这里需要一个头文件
obviously we need our header file there –
Objective-C 中唯一的做法是
the only way to do that in Objective-C is
声明新方法 addCard: 不带 atTop
to declare a new method, add card colon with no at top on it.
这是一个完全不同的方法
So this is a totally different method, totally unrelated
只不过在实现中 我们需要调用另一个方法
to the other method except for that in its implementation
of this other method we’re just going to call the other one.
所以 addCard 中 我们会说 self addCard
So in add card we’re going to say self add card
atTop:
at top colon,
后面跟默认情况 这里也就是 NO
whatever we want the default to be, which I’m going to say is no.
这里只是要你们理解 在某些语言中
So just understand that, you know, in some languages,
某些参数可以是可选的
like, some arguments can be optional or you can kind
或者重载 让相同方法具有不同参数
of overload things to have the same method name have different arguments.
不像 Objective-C 中 每种方法完全不同
No. In Objective-C every method is completely distinct
有不同的名称
and has a distinct name.
多出来的参数会像这样穿插
And extra arguments are interspersed like that.
所以 这是两种不同方法
So these would be two different methods.
能理解吗
That make sense?
好 我们再来看看 Deck 的实现
All right. So let’s talk about our implementation of our deck.
Deck 包含一些纸牌
So our deck is just going to contain a bunch of cards.
我们需要某种内部数据结构来存储所有这些牌
We need some sort of internal data structure to store all our cards in.
我们将会用到的是一个可变数组
And what we’re going do is we’re going to get a mutable array.
你们已经见过 NSArray 类 这是一种基础类数组
So you’ve already seen the class NS array, which is the foundation class array,
其中是一组对象
which is an array of objects.
数组中这些对象可以是任何类的
Those objects, by the way, in array can be of any class.
数组中是哪类对象没法指定
There’s really no way to specify what kind of class of object is in an array.
有些语言让你这样做
Some languages allow you to do that.
你可以指定”这是字符串数组” 它于是知道
You can specify “This is an array of strings” and it knows that.
但 Objective-C 不能这样
But in Objective-C you can’t do that.
我将讲到我们怎么处理这个
And we’re going to talk about how we deal with that.
这在 Objective-C 中有些狂放
That’s a little bit of the wild west of Objective-C,
不过如果想确保安全的话
but there are ways to kind of check and see what the objects
我们有办法检查对象是什么
are if you want to be really safe about it.
而这里 我们用这个可变数组
But in this case we just have this mutable array.
可变意思是说我们可以给数组添加对象
And mutable means that we can add objects to the array.
一般的 NSArray 都是不可变的
Normally an NS array is immutable.
创建后 不管其中放入了什么对象
Once it’s created, whatever objects enter it,
这些对象就永远在里面
that’s the objects that are in it forever –
你无法将它们删除 也无法继续添加
you can’t take any out and you can’t put any in.
如果我们希望数组能添加东西
So if we want array where we can add stuff,
我们需要使用 NSArray 的子类 NSMutableArray
we have to use this subclass of NS array called NS mutable array.
可以看到 它是一个属性
You can see that it’s a property.
它是强的 因为我们希望只要指着数组时
It’s strong because we want this array to stay in the heap
它就应该保留在堆中
as long as we’re pointing at it.
当然 还有我们总会加的非原子性
And of course, we always put nonatomic there.
这就是一个纸牌的数组
So this is going to be an array of cards.
有了这个之后 我们可以轻松实现 addCard
Now that we have this, we could easily implement add card,
例如 我们可以说 “如果在顶部 那么插入对象”
for example, by just saying, “If at top, then insert object,”
card 是这个方法的第一个参数
the card, which is the argument to this method — first argument –
在下标 0 处
”at index zero.”
insertObject atIndex 是 NSMutableArray 中的方法
So insert object at index is a method in NS mutable array,
不是在 NSArray 中 而是 NSMutableArray 中
not in NS array — only in NS mutable array
因为这会让数组变化
because that would be mutating it –
该方法是将对象插入到数组指定下标处
that inserts the object at that index in the array
下标 0 表示是在顶端
and index zero is going to be the top
我们会定义的
that we’re going to define.
如果我们不把它放到顶部 那就放在底部
And then otherwise if we’re not going to put it at the
top, we’re going to put it at the bottom,
这要用到另一个 NSMutableArray 方法 addObject
we’re going to use a different NS mutable array method called add object.
作用是将数组添加到数组末尾
And that just adds something at the end of the array.
大家都明白了吗
So everyone cool with that?
这里给出这些方法只是为了
So I mostly just put this method in here just
展示给你们可变数组的不同方法
to show you there’s a couple of different methods on mutable array and,
以及如何使用参数
you know, how we can use the arguments.
这里并没有什么大不了
It’s no big thing here;
只是为了让你们习惯这里的情况
it’s just kind of to get more used to what’s going on here.
好 这是 addCard 非常非常简单
All right. So that’s add card. Very, very simple.
不过有个问题
And there’s a problem, though.
在这个 addCard 中 如果我们只是创建一个 Deck
In this add card, if we just created a deck
然后调用 addCard 它无法奏效
and then called add card, it would not work.
它什么都做不了
It would do nothing.
为什么呢
Why would it do nothing?
因为属性 cards
Because the property cards, okay –
self.cards 是我们访问属性的方式
self.cards is how we’re accessing our own property –
其 getter 根据默认是那样的
its getter looks like that by default.
如果我们不自定义 getter getter 就是那样
If we don’t give a getter, that’s what the getter looks like.
它会返回这个_cards 实例变量
It’s just going to return this underbar cards instance variable.
而这个_cards 实例变量最开始会是 0
Well, that underbar cards instance variable’s going to start out at zero
因为 Objective-C 中所有实例变量都从 0 开始
because all instance variables in an Objective-C object start out zero.
所有
All of them.
包括指针
So including pointers.
那个指针会是 0 也就是 nil
So that pointer will be zero, which is we call nil,
也就是说它没有指向任何东西 也就是说没有数组
which means it doesn’t point to anything, which means there is no array.
指向数组的指针现在什么都没指到
We got a pointer to an array that doesn’t point to anything right now.
这是一个问题
So that’s a problem.
所以当我们执行 addCard 中
So when we execute the code in add card
self.cards addObject:card 这样的代码时
like self.cards add object card,
程序不会崩溃 但也不会做任何事情
that’s going to not crash but not do anything, either.
因为我说过 你可以将消息发送给 nil
Because I told you that you can send messages to nil,
发送消息给没有指向任何对象的指针
send messages to pointers, to objects where it’s not pointing to one at the time,
这不会崩溃掉
and it will not crash.
如果发送返回某个值的消息 该消息不会执行任何代码
If you send a message that returns a value, that message will not execute any code
它会返回 0
but it will return zero.
这里只是一堆 0 在飞舞
So a lot of zeros flying around here.
这个如何修正呢
So how are we going to fix this?
我们如何让 addCard 工作呢
How are we going make it so that add card works?
我们可以在 addCard 最开始加这样一段
Well, we could put something at the beginning of add card that says,
如果 self.cards 为 nil
”If self.cards is nil,
那么在堆中分配一个数组并指向它 我们会用到它
then go allocate an array in the heap and point to it, and then we’ll use it.”
这就意味着每次使用 self.cards 时
But that would mean every single time we have to use self.cards
我们都需要检验它是否为 nil
we’d have to go around and check and make sure it’s not nil.
这很让人不爽
And that would be very annoying.
这很易于出错 易于产生 bug 我们可能忘记掉
That would be very error-prone, bug-prone, we forget to do it somewhere.
所有这些
All these things.
所以 加入这一段的最佳位置是在 getter 中
So a great place to do that little if check is in the getter.
也就是 cards 的那个 getter
That getter that we have right there for cards –
这是私有属性 cards 的 getter
that’s the getter for our private property cards –
我们让这里不仅仅是返回_cards
instead of just returning the cards,
前面我们再加一行 如果_cards 为 nil
let’s put a line right in front that says, “If the cards is nil,
那么 我们就要在堆中分配空间 并赋值给实例变量
then let’s go allocate one in the heap and assign it to the instance variable.”
这里在堆中分配数组的方式是用
So the way you allocate an array in the heap is
[[NSMutableArray alloc] init]
you use NS mutable array alloc init.
这是两个消息调用嵌套在一起
So that’s two message calls nested inside of each other.
alloc 在堆中分配内存
The alloc allocates the memory in the heap,
init 则用于初始化内存 让它成为一个合理的数组
and init initializes that memory so that it’s a, you know, sensible array.
过几张幻灯片 我会讲到如何构建我们自己的初始化程序
And we’re going to see how we build our own initializer in a couple slides here.
这样一来 每次调用 self.cards 都能保证它不是 nil
So this way every single time you call self.cards, you can be sure that it’s not nil;
它至少会是一个空数组
it’s at least going to be an empty array.
大家都明白这段代码了吗
Does everyone understand this code?
理解这个非常重要 请讲
It’s important to understand this. Yeah.
[学生提问 声音不清]
> [Inaudible]
Paul Hegarty：好 问题是
> Paul Hegarty: Okay. So the question is:
可不可以不将初始化代码放到这个 getter 中
Instead of having this initialization code be in this getter,
而将初始化代码放到 Deck 的 init 中 放到 Deck 中
why don’t I make an initializer like in init for deck and put this inside deck?
这是另一种可选做法
And that is another option.
等下在 PlayingCardDeck 中 我会写一段初始化程序
And again, we’re going to see initializer for playing card deck,
we’re going to make an initializer.
我们可以这样做
And we could do that. But
但让这些的初始化更接近于
having the initialization of this thing be closer
实际获得属性的地方更加…
to the actual getting of the property is more –
它让你的 init 中这样的垃圾更少
it makes your init less full of a bunch of junk like that.
顺便说下 这样做被称作惰性实例化
And this is called lazy instantiation, by the way, doing it this way.
我们是惰性地等到最后一秒再实例化
We are lazily waiting to the last second until we instantiate.
这种做法是 Objective-C 中每个人都习惯的
This pattern is something everyone in Objective-C is used to,
你们也应当用这个 而不是写到 init 中
and you should definitely use it rather than doing things in your init.
init 中 你希望设置各种
In init you want to, you know, set things, set values that,
不能简单像这样初始化的值
you know, can’t easily be defaulted like this.
不过你问得很好
But that’s a very good question.
过几张幻灯我们就会看到 init
And we’ll see init in a couple slides.
这样我们就保证了 self.cards 不为 nil 请讲
So this way we’re guaranteed self.cards is never nil. Yeah?
[学生提问 声音不清]
> [Inaudible]
Paul Hegarty：对 下划线来自上一讲
> Paul Hegarty: Yeah. So the underscore is from last lecture.
记得吧 当我们创建一个属性时
Remember that when we create a property,
Objective-C 会自动给出
Objective-C automatically does this thing,
@synthesize cards = _cards
@synthesize cards equals underbar cards.
也就是说 这赋值了一个实例变量 叫下划线属性名
So in other words, it assigns an instance variable called underbar name of property
作为该属性的存储空间
to be the storage space for that property.
因此_cards 是自动创建的 这是幕后完成的
So that’s why underbar cards are automatically created for us there behind the scenes.
@synthesize 没出现在我的代码里 但它确实存在
That at sign synthesizes a pop up in our code, but it’s there behind the scenes.
问得很好
That’s a very good question.
这里还有问题吗
Any other questions about this?
好 下面继续来看随机抽取纸牌方法
Okay. So let’s collapse down some of this stuff and look at draw a random card.
随机抽取纸牌希望从 self.cards 中随机抽选一张牌
So draw a random card, all it wants to do is get a random card out of that self.cards.
代码很简单
So that code is very simple as well.
我们获取一个随机整数
So we just get a random integer.
arc4random 就是做这个的 它是一个 C 库函数
That’s what arc 4 random does if you don’t know. It’s just a C library function.
用于获取一个随机整数
It gets a random integer.
之后的 % 表示求余数
Then that little percent after it means mod — okay, integer modulo –
然后 self.cards count 是
and then self.cards count is
self.cards 中纸牌的数目
the number of cards in our self.cards.
这就得到随机数 index 作为 self.cards 的下标
So we’re just going to get a random index into self.cards,
然后赋值给 randomCard
then assign a random card
= self.cards[index]
to be self.cards square brackets index.
这里方括号是数组访问的标准语法
So this is that same square brackets to access an array kind of syntax.
有趣的是 self.cards[index] 实际上
And it’s interesting, that self.cards square brackets index, actually,
也是一个消息发送 信不信由你
that’s a message send believe it or not.
这等价于 self.cards objectAtIndex:index
That’s same as self.cards object at index index.
这里只是一种特殊的语法甜头
It’s just some special syntax and syntactic sugar
这样你就不需要写很长的 objectAtIndex 了
to make it so that you don’t have to have long object at index.
不需要 objectAtIndexedSubscript 这样的长方法名
It’s actually object at subscripted index or something with a real long method name.
这里只是一些简短美妙的语法
So this is just a beautiful, little simple syntax.
不过这是一种消息发送 来得到数组该下标处的牌
But that is a message send to get the card at that index out of the array.
然后我们还要从数组中删除这张牌
And then we’re also going to remove that card out of the array
因为这张牌已经被抽出
because this is draw a random card.
抽出后就不在这一叠牌中了
It’s draw the card out of the deck. So it’s not in the deck anymore, right?
这段代码也有问题 也就是
Now, there’s a problem with this code as well, which is:
如果这一叠牌是空的怎么办
What if the deck is empty?
如果这一叠牌是空的 那么 unsigned index 将是 0
If the deck is empty, then that unsigned index is going to be zero,
这里将是 arc4random % 0
right, because it’s going to be arc 4 random mod zero.
这将是 0
That’s going to be zero.
于是后面就是 randomCard = self.cards[0]
And so you’re going to say, “Random card equals self.card sub zero.”
这会让你的程序崩溃掉
Well, that’s going to crash your program
因为 self.cards 是一个空数组
because if self.cards is an empty array,
那么下标 0 处将没有对象 这是数组下标越界错误
then there’s no object at index zero and you’re going to get array index out of bounds.
小心这个
So be careful of that.
数组在某下标处没有对象时 你就无法得到它
The index — you cannot get the index — if an array doesn’t have an object
of that index, you can’t get it.
这很好修正
So that’s easy to fix, though.
我们可以加上 if ([self.cards count])
We’re just going to say, “If self.cards count,”
也就是说 如果数组中有内容 那么我们就这样做
in other words if there are things in the array, “then we’ll do that.
否则我们将返回 randomCard
Otherwise we’re just going to return random card,” which I
方法最开始时我就已经将其初始化为 nil 了
happily initialized to nil at the beginning of my method.
所以我喜欢这样做
And that’s why I kind of like this thing of
初始化得到你想要的默认值
initialize it to the default value you want,
然后设置 然后返回
then set it, and then return.
这样一来 如果设置不幸失败的话
And that way if the setting fails for some reason
例如像这样 一叠牌根本就没牌
like this — it fails because there’s no cards in the deck –
它会返回合适的默认值
it will return the reasonable default.
这是一种编程风格
That’s just kind of a coding style thing.
我们对 score 和 match 也做了相同的事情
We did that same thing with score and match.
关于这个有问题吗 请讲
Any questions about that? Yeah?
[学生提问 声音不清]
[Inaudible]
Paul Hegarty：问得很好
> Paul Hegarty: Great question.
问题是 什么时候用 NSInteger 或 NSUInteger
So the question is: When do I use NS integer or NSU integer
而不用 int 甚至我们还没讲到过的 NSNumber
versus int or even NS number, which is an object which we haven’t talked about yet?
答案是 这是一个风格问题
And the answer is it’s a matter of style.
我会简单讲到这种风格 以及何时使用这些
And we’ll talk a little bit about that style and when to use these things.
只是在局部使用时
Here I don’t really want to use an NS number which is an object
不要用 NSNumber 这种对象
when I’m just using it, you know, as a little local thing like that.
不要那样
You would never do that.
使用 NSNumber 通常是为了将其传递给方法
You’re using NS numbers basically to pass them to methods.
哪怕这时你也可以传递 int 或 float 值
And even then you could pass ints, you know, and floats.
下周讲 NSNumber 时这会变得很明显
So it will be become obvious as I talk about NS number, which we’ll do next week.
这是 Deck
Okay. So that’s it for deck.
Deck 也是很简单的类
Deck, very simple class as well.
下面看另一个类 也就是 PlayingCard
So let’s move onto another class, which is playing card.
我展示 PlayingCard
The reason I’m showing you playing cards,
是为了跟你们讲解某一类的子类怎么写
I just want to show you what it looks like to make a subclass
of another class that you’ve written.
PlayingCard 是 Card 的子类
So playing card is a subclass of card.
它专指扑克牌 例如红心 K
And this is the specific card like king of hearts,
方片 3 这些牌
three of diamonds, that kind of card.
PlayingCard 具有特有属性 suit 和 rank
Now, it has properties that are specific to a playing card, which is the suit and rank.
rank 也就是大小 3 4 J K 这些
The rank being like a three, four, a jack, king, right?
suit 是花色 红心 方片 梅花
And the suit being hearts, diamonds, clubs.
我将用单字符表示 suit
And I’m going to represent the suit as a single character –
红心字符 梅花字符
the hearts characters, the clubs character.
我好像展示过扑克牌中梅花字符的输入
Remember I typed the clubs character I think in the card we might have shown that.
反正 你可以输入一个字符
I don’t know. But you can type a single character.
Unicode 对这四种花色都有相应字符
Unicode has a character for each of the four suits.
这是 suit
So that’s what my suit is going to be.
而 rank 是从 0 到 13 数字
And then the rank is going to be a number between zero and thirteen.
13 表示 K
Is that king?
这些表示大小
Yeah. Representing the rank.
这就是公共 API 中的表示
So that’s how I’m going to represent in my public API.
注意这里我用的是 NSUInteger
And here I’m using notice NSU integer
而不是 unsigned int
instead of unsigned int.
NSUInteger 和 unsigned int 几乎是一回事
So NSU integer and unsigned int are almost exactly the same thing.
NSUInteger 唯一不同的是 它是一个 typedef
The only thing about NSU integer is it’s typedef.
它在不同平台下可能略有不同
It might be a little different on different platforms.
例如新的 iPhone 5S 是 64 位处理器
For example, the new iPhone 5s are 64-bit processers.
所以 NSUInteger 是 64 位无符号整型
So NSU integer is going to be a 64-bit int, unsigned int on an iPhone 5.
而之前的 iPhone 则只有 32 位
And it might only about a 32-bit one back on an iPhone 4 and before.
这里有些不同
So that’s a little bit different.
很细枝末节
So a minor nit.
我们可能要不了那么大的整数
We were probably not representing integers.
显然 这里只是从 0 到 13
Certainly here we’re only going zero to thirteen.
问题不大
Probably doesn’t matter.
要知道 我们用不到 33 位那么大的数
But, you know, we’re not representing integers that are so gigantic
that we’re going to be using the 33rd bit.
注意到 PlayingCard 中
So notice that in playing card
我们重写了 Card 方法 contents
we’re overriding card method contents.
我们从父类继承了 contents
We inherit contents from our superclass.
根据默认 contents 仅仅返回
And by default contents just returns
contents 属性的值
the value of whatever the contents property is.
但这里在 PlayingCard 中 我们将重写 contents
But here in the playing card we’re going to override contents
基于其它两个属性来实际计算 contents
to actually calculate our contents, based on these other two properties.
我们重写 contents 的 getter
So we’re overriding the getter of contents
也就是这张扑克牌的内容
so that it always returns a string –
让它总是返回一个计算自花色和大小的字符串
the contents of this playing card — that is calculated from the suit and rank.
明白吗
You see what we’re doing here?
我们从父类取存储 contents 的_contents
So we’re basically taking the storage of contents — underbar contents –
然后忽略它
from our superclass and ignoring it
因为我们重写了其 getter
because we’re overriding its getter.
这就是使用这些属性的一个很好理由
So this is a perfectly valid reason why we do these properties as well
因为我们可能有比单纯存储更好的做法
because we might have a better way to do things than the storage.
这是可以进行实现的方式 我们可以返回一个字符串
Now, here’s a way we could implement it: We can just return a string.
NSString stringWithFormat
NS string, string with format
类似于 printf 一个字符串
just like printf-ing a string.
别太担心这里的语法
Don’t worry about that syntax too much.
printf 字符串的格式是 %d%@
And I’m printf-ing a string with percent D and percent at sign.
%d 表示整数 %@表示一个对象
So percent D means integer; percent at sign means an object.
一个对象的字符串表示
A string representation of an object.
然后我将使用 rank 和 suit
And then I’m just using the rank and suit.
这是处理 contents 的一种方式
So this would be one way to do my contents.
这不是一个很好的方式 因为
It’s not a very good way because, for example,
例如红心 J 是 11 红心
the jack of hearts would say 11 hearts.
至少 J 我们想用 J 而不是 11
It’s not going to say J at least; we want to say J, not 11.
这个方式不怎么好
So this is not a very good way.
所以我想让一个数组中
So instead I’m going to make an array
有所有正确的东西 比如 A 表示 1
that has all the right things like an A for a one,
J 表示 11 Q 表示 12 K 表示 13
and a J for 11, and a Q for 12, and a K for 13, right?
这里我创建一个数组
So I’m just making this array here.
中间我需要删去 让它能够显示出来
In the middle there I had to cut out to make it fit, right?
我还让 0 为问号
And I even made zero be question mark.
如果 rank 为 0 它会是问号 如未设
So if your rank is zero, it’s going to be, like, question mark, like, unset.
大小没有设定
You know, your rank is basically not set.
然后我返回一个字符串
And then I return a string,
它会取出那个数组中的 rank
which is taking the rank out of that array
然后追加表示 suit 的字符串
and appending onto it the little suit string,
红心 梅花 方片这些
the heart, or the club, or the diamond.
都明白吗
Everyone understand this?
给你们讲这些是为了让你们明白
I’m kind of giving you this so you can see how we’re mixing
如何无缝混合数组符号 消息发送所有这些东西
in the array notation, and message sending, and it all kind of seamlessly mixes in there.
这时 contents 会返回 J 红心 或 5 方块这些
So now contents returns J hearts, or 5 diamonds, or whatever.
注意到 rank 很棒
Notice that our rank is really nice
因为在我们说 new PlayingCard 时 rank 会为 0
because if our rank is zero, which it starts out being when we say new playing card –
所有实例变量为 0 所以 rank 为 0
all the instance variables are zero so rank would be zero –
我们得到这个问号
we get this nice question mark.
但 suit 开始时是 nil
But our suit starts out as nil,
如果 suit 在未设或为 nil 时也能返回问号就好了
and it would be nice if the suit also returned question mark if it was unset, if it was nil.
所以这里我重写 suit 的 getter 如下
So here I’m just overriding the getter of suit to say,
如果 suit 是 nil 那么返回问号
”If return, if my suit is nil, then return the question mark,
否则当 suit 不是 nil 时 那么返回 suit 的实际值
otherwise when my suit’s not nil, then return what the suit is.”
我是在保护我的 API
So I’m just kind of protecting my API
保证我在 rank 或 suit 未设时 总是返回问号
to make sure I always return question mark when the rank or suit is not set.
请讲
Yeah.
[学生提问 声音不清]
> [Inaudible]
Paul Hegarty：抱歉 你是说的红色 @号吗
> Paul Hegarty: Sorry. All little at signs — the red at signs, you mean?
对 我们在 Card 中应该没碰到过这个
Yeah. Guess we didn’t get to that in card.
也可能碰到过
But we might have. But
记得吧
remember that
我们这门课碰到的所有字符串都是字符串对象
all strings that we’re going to work with in this class are string objects,
而非 const char
not const char stars.
它们是字符串对象
They’re string objects.
如果你在字符串前加一个 @
And the compiler, if you put an at sign in front of a string,
编译器会为你创建字符串对象
it will make a string object for you.
这些 @的作用是让所有字符串为字符串对象
So that’s what those at signs do, they make all those strings be string objects
因为我们不能将 const char * 放到 NSArray 中
because we can’t put a const char star in an NS array.
NSArray 中只能是对象 所以只能用 NSString 这些
NS array is for objects, so we have to put objects in there like NS strings.
这些才是对象 问得很好
Those are objects. Good question.
请讲
Yeah?
[学生提问 声音不清]
[Inaudible]
Paul Hegarty：对 好 问得很好
> Paul Hegarty: Yes. Okay. That’s a good question.
如果我们用了 getter= 符号
If we had used that getter equals notation that we used
就像 isChosen 和 isMatched 那样 来改名
for is chosen and is matched to change the name,
那么重写时 我们就需要使用新名
then when we override we have to use the new name.
我们就需要用 is 什么 这里不需要那样
We’d have to is whatever. Now, this is not the case here.
但我知道你说的是什么 对 你需要用新名
But I know what you’re saying, and yes, you would have to use the new name.
问得很好
Great question.
这方面还有问题吗
Any other questions about this?
好 这能帮助 suit 在为 nil 或未设时总是返回问号
Okay. So that helps the suit always return question mark if the suit is nil or not set.
我们再加一层保护 以防有人错误设置了 suit
Let’s also protect people setting the suit to something wrong.
我们将只让人使用属性的公共 setter 来设置 suit
Let’s only let people set the suit using this property,
the public setter of the property.
suit 将只被允许设置为四种花色之一
We’ll only let people set the suit to be one of the four suits.
我简单在这里创建了四种花色的数组
So I just on the fly in the middle there created an array of those four suits.
然后用到方法 containsObject
And then I use this method contains object;
从这里看 你们觉得 containsObject 是什么
what class do you think contains object is from that bit on?
谁讲讲
Anyone?
[学生提问 声音不清]
> [Inaudible]
Paul Hegarty：这是一种 NSArray 方法 正确
> Paul Hegarty: It’s an NS array method, exactly.
containsObject 是一种 NSArray 方法
So contains object is an NS array method.
我将它送往我刚创建的数组
I’m sending it to the array that I create right in place there.
包含红心 方片 黑桃 梅花的那个数组
The array that has hearts, diamonds, spades, and clubs in it.
我问 你是否包含这个字符串
And I’m just asking: Do you contain this string?
containsObject 会使用 isEqual 方法对比
And that contains object is going to compare the contents
这个字符串的内容和所有这些
of this string against all these using a method is equal.
它会将 suit 作为参数用 isEqual 一一对比四个字符串
Actually, it’s going to say is equal to all four of them with the suit as the argument;
不是 isEqualToString 而是 isEqual
not is equal to string — is equal.
isEqual 是由 isEqualToString 来实现的
And in string is equal is implemented by calling is equal
如果参数是字符串的话
to string if the argument’s a string.
这里讲了太多无关紧要的细节
Anyway, more detail than you need probably there.
这里显然能起到保护作用
But this is obviously protecting it.
这样内部花色存储变量就无法设置为
So there’s no way we can set our internal suit storage variable
这四种花色以外任何东西了 请讲
to anything except for those four suits. Yeah?
[学生提问 声音不清]
[Inaudible]
Paul Hegarty：问得很棒 你们理解得真不错
> Paul Hegarty: Great question. You guys are right on top of it.
每次我使用 @[这样的符号
So every time I use the at sign open square bracket --
如这里蓝色的部分
the blue one -- to
这实际是在创建新数组 每次都是这样
create an array, that's actually creating a new array every time.
因为我讲过 @[…]
Because I told you that that at sign square bracket
及所有这些数组东西 只是在调用方法
and all this array stuff is really just calling methods?
这就像是调用数组 对象这些的 alloc init 方法
Well, that’s calling a method like alloc init with array
with objects or something like that.
这是在创建
Right? So it is creating it.
将它移出来也很好 我们会这样做
So it would be nice to move it out, and we’re going to do that.
不过 注意不要预优化
Although, again, be careful not to preoptimize.
它可能不会有任何不同
It probably wouldn’t make any different.
移出来只是为了让代码更简洁
I’m only going to move it out to make my code cleaner;
移出来不是出于任何性能考虑 请讲
I’m not going to move it out for any performance reason. Yeah?
[学生提问 声音不清]
> [Inaudible]
Paul Hegarty：问题是
> Paul Hegarty: The question is:
LLVM 会处理这个 为你优化好吗
Would LLVM just take care of that, optimize that out for you?
它可能不会 因为这是一个消息发送
And it probably wouldn’t because that’s a message send;
它不确定这样有没有副作用
it’s not sure what there might be side effects of it.
无论如何 我们这样做是为了让代码更简洁
But in any case, we’re just going to do it just to make our code look cleaner.
性能在这里可以忽略
And the performance would be negligible here.
我们讲的是 UI 这相差很远
We’re talking about UI. It’s not even close.
在这之前 还有一点要讲
One thing to note, though, before we do that is
由于我们现在已经实现了 suit 的 setter 和 getter
since we’ve implemented both the setter and the getter of suit,
这就必须处理 @synthesize 了
we are now required to do the at sign synthesize.
换言之 一般我们不需要处理 @synthesize
In other words, normally we don’t have to do this at sign synthesize.
它会自动生成
It gets done for us.
但当同时实现 setter 和 getter 时 就需要处理了
But if we implement both the setter and the getter, now we do.
这很容易 因为形式总是一样
It’s easy to do because it’s always of this exact same form.
但容易也需要做
But we do have to do it.
这里 做我刚才讲的事情
Okay. So here’s — let’s do what we were saying.
我们将花色的数组放入到另一个方法中
Let’s take that little array of suits we have in there and put it in another method.
我说过 这样做不会有任何性能好处
Now, again, I’m not getting any performance by doing this.
这样做只是代码更简洁一些
I’m just getting code cleanliness by doing this
因为每次调用 validSuits 时还是会重新创建
because I’m still — every time I call valid suits, it’s going to create it again.
我可以使用一个静态变量
Now, I could use a static variable.
这是 C 我可以存储这个数组
This is C. I could store this array.
开始是 nil
Started out being nil.
如果是 nil 设置到这个数组 然后它只会创建一次
If it’s nil, set it to this array, and then it would only create it once.
但要小心
But be careful.
还是那句话 代码简洁性
Again, code cleanliness
还有易理解性 比这样的性能重要十倍
and understandably ten times more important than performance like this.
只要你不是在循环中上千次地调用 validSuits
So unless you’re going to call valid suits in the inner loop thousands of times,
这个影响都很小
it’s not really going to matter.
我把它往上移动到一个不同方法中
But once I move that up into a different method,
但这个方法有些不同
this kind of method that I moved it to is a little different.
注意到它前面是个加号
Notice it has a plus.
最开始是加号 而不是减号 看到了吗
You see a plus there instead of a minus starting it?
+ (NSArray *)validSuits
Plus NS array valid suits?
+ 方法是一个类方法
Okay. A plus method is a class method.
这意味着你将它发送给类 而不是对象实例
That means you send it to the class, not to an instance of an object.
因为不是发送给一个实例
So since you’re not sending it to an instance,
所以你不能使用任何实例变量
you can’t use any instance variables or anything like that.
你只能做一些通用性的事情
You can only just kind of do generic stuff.
实际上 + 方法 类方法只用于两种情况
So the only thing we really use plus methods for, class methods, is two things really:
创建事物
Creating things
例如上一张幻灯片中我们有带格式的字符串时
like in the previous slide when we had string with format –
这是类方法 为我们创建一个字符串
that’s a class method that was creating a string for us;
然后就是这样的工具方法
and then also utility methods like this,
例如返回常数
like the return constants
还有其它我们的类需要工具方法的情况
and things that, you know, our class wants and utility methods.
这是一个例子
But here’s an example.
再看调用类方法的方式
And the way we call the class method –
你们已经看过我调用了一些
you’ve already seen me call a few of them –
这里就是在调用它 首先是开方括号
but here’s calling it here is we put open square bracket,
然后是类名 然后是方法名
the name of the class, the name of the method.
同其它方法一样 它也可以有参数
And again, it could have arguments. It’s just like any other method.
大家都能理解吗
But everyone understand this?
好 回头几张幻灯片
Okay. And if you go back and look a couple slides
你会看到 [NSString 带格式的字符串
and you see open square bracket NS string, string with format,
完全相同的语法
same exact type of syntax.
这就是类方法的样子
So that's what a class method looks like.
用于创建事物 以及用作工具方法
Again, for creating things basically and for utility methods.
我们会谈到
And we'll talk about the difference of:
用类方法创建和用 alloc init 创建的不同
When do we create something with a class method versus alloc init?
不久后我就会讲到
We'll talk about that soon.
我还让 validSuits 是公共的
I'm also going to make valid suits public.
这样 PlayingCard 的使用者就知道 validSuits 是什么
And that way people who are using my playing card know what the valid suits are.
我只需要把它放到头文件中
And all I need to do is put it in the header file.
现在就是公共的了
Boom, it's public now.
这里对扑克牌大小字符串也做相同的事情
So let's do a similar thing here with those rank strings.
我将把上面的大小字符串
So I'm going to take those ranks strings -- that array of rank strings right up there --
放入到一个类方法中
and I'm going to put that in a class method.
还是那句话 这是为了可读性 而非性能
And again, this is for readability, not for performance.
因为每次调用 rankStrings 这都会重新创建
Because every time I call rank strings, it's still going to create that thing again.
然后 我在这上面调用它
And then I call it instead up there.
我不打算让 rankStrings 本身成为公共的
And I'm not going to make rank strings itself public,
但我打算让另一个类方法 maxRank 成为公共的
but I am going to make another class method called max rank,
这个方法考虑的是 rankStrings 中有多少字符串
which just looks at how many strings are in rank strings.
我将把这作为公共方法返回
And I'm going to return that as a public method.
这里有三个类方法 让你们钻研
So there's three class methods for you to sink your teeth
两个是公共的 一个不是
into -- two of them public, one not.
这些都是工具方法
All right. And so they're all utility methods, right?
我们没有在任何这些方法中访问任何实例变量
We're not accessing any instance variables in any of those methods.
我讲这些的唯一原因
That's the only reason I'm showing those,
就是让你们了解类方法是怎样的
is just so you see what a class method looks like.
我们还可以重写 rank 的 setter
We also could override the setter of rank just
来保证这里不允许
to be complete here to make sure it doesn't allow you
设置错误的大小 例如 15
to set a wrong rank like set rank 15 --
没有大小为 15 的牌
there's no such card as 15.
我们需要确保大小小于最大大小
So let's make sure that the rank is less than the max rank,
刚那个工具方法做了这个
which is the utility method we just did.
大家都理解了吗
Does that all come together for you, make sense?
这里只是参考材料
So this is kind of reference material.
你们的幻灯片中 有我讲的所有这些注释
You have these slides that have all the annotations of all the things I'm saying.
你们可以回头看幻灯片当作复习
So feel free to go back and look at it and remind yourself
关于这些 NSArray 语法
about all these NS array, syntax,
这些类方法 等等
and all the class methods, all that stuff.
最后我们要看的是 init 方法
Okay. The last thing we're going to look at is the init method business.
这里我们还有一个类叫 PlayingCardDeck
So we're going to have another class here called playing card deck.
PlayingCardDeck 是 Deck 的一个子类
And a playing card deck is a subclass of deck.
它没有公共 API
And it has no public API.
它将只是重写一个间接继承自 NSObject 的方法
It's just going to override a method that it inherits indirectly from NS object --
NSObject 通过 Deck 这里没动它
okay, NS object through deck, which doesn't touch it --
直到 PlayingCardDeck
all the way to playing card deck.
这个方法叫作 init
And that method is called init.
这个 init 同之前我们创建那个可变数组时所说的
So this is the same init, same kind of method that when we created that array --
[NSMutableArray alloc] init 中的 init 一样
that mutable array we said NS mutable array alloc init.
有人需要调用这个 PlayingCardDeck init 方法
so someone is going to call this PlayingCardDeck init method –
也就是你们 在作业中
namely you in your homework
会通过 PlayingCardDeck alloc 调用这个
are going to call this by doing playing card deck alloc,
然后外面再写 init
and then on the outside, init.
这就是创建一个 PlayingCardDeck 的方式
And that’s how you’re going to create a playing card deck.
这就是我们创建大多数对象实例的方式 并非所有
And that is how we create most instances of objects — not all.
有时我们会使用 NSString 带格式的字符串
Sometimes we do things like the NS string, string with format.
但大多数时候 大于一半的时候
But most of the time — more than half the time –
我们会用 alloc 然后外面用 init
we do alloc and then on the outside init.
听好
Listen carefully:
除了外面有 init 时 永远别调用 alloc 那些东西
Never call that alloc thing without wrapping an init around it.
不要犯忌
Don’t ever do that.
不初始化就分配对象在堆中毫无意义
That makes no sense to have an object allocated in the heap that’s never been initialized.
只有嵌套才对
Always have that nested.
反之 除了里面有 alloc 外面也不要调用 init
And vice versa: Never call that init except for when you wrap it around an alloc.
而且一定不要超过一次地调用 init
And definitely never call that init more than once.
如果你按照我说的 只在里面有 alloc 时才调用
And if you obey my rule of only calling it wrapped around an alloc,
调用就不可能超过一次
you can’t call it more than once.
init 没有说你能重新 init 的
Init is not something like you can re-init.
init 只能发生一次 紧接 alloc 之后 这就完了
Init happens once right after alloc, and that’s it.
这是一条硬性规定 永远不要违反
That is a hard and fast rule we never break.
这里我讲了
So you heard it here.
别忘记
Don’t forget.
好 我们来看看这个 init 方法的怪异返回类型
All right. Let’s look at the whacky return type to this init method.
你也许会以为 init 方法会返回一个 PlayingCardDeck
You might think this init method should return a playing card deck star
因为它在初始化 也许会返回它自身
because it’s kind of initializing and maybe it returns itself.
实际上 init 确实总返回 self
And in fact, init does always return self.
init 总会返回自身
So init is always going to return self.
这里比较怪异 我会讲到
Okay. More whackiness there, which I’m going to describe.
方便起见 它总返回 self 让你能够写
Just for convenience, it always returns self so that you can do,
[PlayingCardDeck alloc] init 这些 发送一条消息
like, playing card deck alloc init, sent it a message.
它返回 self 是很方便的
So it’s just convenience that it returns self.
但它的返回类型不能是 PlayingCardDeck
But it can’t really have its return type being playing card deck star
因为这些它继承于 NSObject
because it inherited this from NS object.
而 NSObject 已经将其定义为 NSObject
And NS object already defined it as NS object star.
明白吗 所以说有些奇怪
You see? So it’s kind of weird
你继承了一个方法 其返回值
that you’re inheriting a method whose return value would have
需要在每次重写时发生变化
to change every time you, you know, overrode it.
于是人们发明了这个新东西 这是 iOS7 的新属性
So they invented this new thing — this is new for iOS 7, by the way –
叫实例类型
called instance type.
实例类型也就是说
And what instance type means is this is going
这会返回一个对象 具有相同类类型
to return an object that is of the same instance — same type, same class type –
同这条消息要发送到的对象一样
as the object you sent this message to.
这对 init 很有意义
Which makes perfect sense for inits.
这门课上 只有这里会用到这个
And in this class that’s probably all you’re going to use this for right here.
听不懂我刚讲的这些不要紧 我在幻灯片中也讲了
So if you don’t really understand what I just said — it’s explained in the slides –
but if you don’t really understand it,
你只需知道 凡是初始化时
just know that whenever you do an initializer,
它都会返回实例类型作为返回类型
it’s going to return instance type as its return type
你将总是返回 self
and you’re always going to return self.
还有一点 也是记住就行
Now, also just take my word for it.
后面这几行代码也非常奇怪
We’re going to do these next lines of codes as well because they are really strange.
第一行 self = [super init] 这很奇怪
That first line, self equals super init, that is weird.
这非常奇怪
That is super weird.
Objective-C 中将什么东西复制给 self
Assigning something to self in Objective-C –
永远不要这样做 唯独除了 init 里
just never do that, except for this one time and that’s in your init.
对 self 赋值 调用父类初始化器
You take self and you assign it to calling your superclasses initializer
于是父类会被初始化
so that your superclass gets initialized.
为什么将结果赋值给 self 呢
Why do we assign the result to self?
可以说是古老的历史残留
It’s kind of ancient history
因为人们这样做了很长时间
as to why this has been done for a long time.
一般 我们会检验父类 init 的返回
Basically we’re checking the return of our superclasses init
确保它正确被初始化
to make sure it properly initialized.
因为任何初始化器无法初始化自身的时候
Because at any time if your initializer cannot initialize itself,
它应返回 nil
it should return nil.
这让所有人知道 你的任意子类
And that lets everybody know any of your subclasses
或任何人尝试分配和初始化你
or anyone trying to alloc and initialize you,
你无法创建一个结构良好的对象
you could not create a well-formed object.
你可以看到 这个代码很奇怪
So you can see how this code, strange as it is –
self = [super init] 然后 if (self)
self equals super init, and then if self,
我将初始化自身 返回 self
I’m going to initialize myself, return self –
这将能确保 当我的父类在我调用 init 时
that’s going to ensure that I don’t even try to initialize myself if my superclass,
如果无法初始化自身 我就不用尝试初始化我自己
when I call its init, you know, can’t initialize itself.
照做就行了
So just do it.
不懂不要紧 照做就行了
If you don’t understand it, don’t worry about it too much. Just do it.
有一点我要讲明 init 没有参数
Now, one thing here is we’re talking about init with no arguments.
让初始化器有参数是完全有可能的
It is possible to have initializers with arguments
因为有时你需要参数来恰当地初始化一个类
because sometimes you need arguments to properly initialize a class.
周一我会进一步讲到这个
And we’re going to talk about that a little more on Monday.
今天只讲解 init 的梗概
So today we’re just going to kind of bare bones init.
这个 init 需要做什么
So what does this init need to do?
我需要怎样做
What do I need to do
才能得到初始化良好的 PlayingCardDeck
to have a well-formed initialized playing card deck?
PlayingCardDeck 有 52 张牌 一样一张
Well, a playing card deck has 52 cards in it, one of each kind of card.
梅花 K 方片 3 总共 52 张
King of clubs, three of diamonds — all 52 of them.
我只需要遍历所有花色 遍历所有大小
So I just need to iterate to all the suits, and then iterate through all the ranks,
创建一张牌 然后添加到我自身
and create a card, and add it to myself.
这里我遍历花色 遍历大小
So here’s me iterating through the suits, iterating through the ranks.
大家都明白吗
Everyone cool with that?
然后我将导入 PlayingCard
Then I’m going to import playing card
因为我要创建一张 PlayingCard
because I’m going to create a playing card,
[PlayingCard alloc] init
playing card alloc init.
然后我要设置这张牌的大小 设置花色
Then I’m going to set that card’s rank, set that card’s suit.
rank 和 suit 是这里的迭代变量
Rank and suit are my little iteration variables there.
然后我把它加到我自身
And then I’m going to add it to myself.
我是一个 Deck 这很好
I’m a deck, so that’s perfectly fine.
大家都明白这段代码吗
Everybody cool with that code?
现在我就得到一个结构良好的 PlayingCardDeck
So now I’m a well-formed playing card deck and I can be used
可以被用于随机抽取纸牌 等等动作
to draw random cards and all that stuff,
这将是你们的作业内容
which you will need to do for your homework.
实际上 你们的作业是将所有这四个类补全
And in fact, for your homework you’re going to have to type all four of these classes in.
我希望你们体会到录入类 键入内容
I want you to get experience entering classes, typing a thing,
观看 Xcode 抱怨你的错误 等等
watching as Xcode complains at you as you mistype things, and stuff like that.
然后你们将会使用 PlayingCardDeck 和 PlayingCard
And then you’re going to be using playing card deck and playing card.
PlayingCardDeck 和 Card 是你们作业中
Well, playing card deck and card really are the two main ones
主要要用到的两个类
you’re going to be using to do your homework.
对此有问题吗
Questions about that?
幻灯片就到这里
Okay. So that’s it for the slides.
下面我将给出一个大而古老的 demo
So now I’m going to do a big old demo.
这个 demo 将综合你们到目前为止看到过的一切
And this demo is going to integrate everything you’ve seen so far.
尤其是我们谈过的 MVC 内容
Most notably that MVC stuff we talked about,
例如目标动作 设置目标 发射动作
like target action, you know, dropping the target and shooting the action
还有绿色箭头的 outlet 指向相反方向
or the green arrow outlet that points the other way.
我们会展示这些在 Xcode 中是怎样
We’re going to show you what that actually looks like in Xcode.
我问你们谁用过 Xcode 时
I think when I asked who of you have done Xcode,
几乎所有人都举手了
almost every single one of you raised your hands.
所以我不打算讲解 Xcode 中的所有按钮
So I’m not going to spend too much time talking about all the buttons in Xcode.
我将很快略过这些
I think I’ll quickly pass over those.
没有用过 Xcode 的人 课程幻灯片中有详细介绍
But if you haven’t used Xcode, it’s in very much detail in the lecture slides.
你们可以看看
There’s kind of this walkthrough.
你可以跟随课程幻灯片一起看
By the way, if you’re following along in the lecture slides,
不过我的 demo 同幻灯片中不完全一样
my demo’s not going to be exactly like what’s in the slides.
幻灯片要多于我这里 40 分钟可以讲的内容
The slides cover a little bit more than I can cover in forty minutes here.
而且它也是参考材料
And it’s also reference material.
如果我在 demo 中讲的东西让你觉得
So if I do something today in this demo and you’re like,
哦 他怎么做的
”Oh, how did he do that?”
你可以去查幻灯片 它会告诉你
if you go look in those slides, it will tell you.
所以不要觉得 我要逐一记下
So do not feel like, “I got to furiously write
他在这 40 分钟里面要讲的每一个细节
down every button click he’s going to do in the next forty minutes.”
不用这样
No way. Okay?
你可以边看幻灯片边看 demo
Follow along in those slides if you want,
也可以关掉笔记本 只看我讲 然后理解
or just close your laptop, and watch, and let it sink in
因为你们作业中需要再现
because you’re going to have to reproduce what I’m doing
我这 40 分钟所要讲的内容
in the next forty minutes for your homework.
而幻灯片中会一步步告诉你怎么做
And those slides are going to walk you through step by step how to do it.
现在你们什么都不需要做 只需要仔细听我讲
So do not feel like you need to do anything right now but let this all sink in.
感受一下发生了什么
Get a feel for what’s going on.
然后当你要坐下来做时 还有幻灯片可查
And then when you sit down to do it, you’ll be guided through it.
下周 我将更详细讲到 Objective-C
Next week we’re going to talk a lot more about Objective-C,
详细回答 NSNumber 等同学们提出的一些问题
answer some of these more detailed questions
like NS number and some of these other things people are asking.
而且我会讲到 Objective-C 中的一些特定内容
And we’ll talk about some of the specific things about Objective-C
例如动态绑定 协议
like dynamic binding, and protocols,
这些东西一般在其它语言中是没有的
and things that you don’t generally see as much
in other languages or don’t exist in other languages.
我会讲给你们
So we’ll try and cover all that.
在下周末最后 等你们熟悉了 Objective-C
So by the end of next week you’re up to speed in Objective-C.
熟悉了 Xcode
You’re starting to really run with Xcode.
之后我们就可以开始真正做点什么了
And so the week after that we can really start doing some,
进行强大的 iOS7 编程
you know, high power iOS 7 stuff.
好 开始 demo
Okay. So demo here.
demo 我将用 Xcode 来进行
So the demo I’m going to run in Xcode.
启动 Xcode
So I’m just going to launch Xcode.
Xcode 需要到 Mac app 商店
So Xcode you get by running — going to your Mac app store.
也就是这个
That’s this thing down here, right?
用 Mac 登陆 app 商店 然后搜索 Xcode
Get the app store on your Mac, and you just search for Xcode, find it.
它是免费的 下载运行即可 很简单
It’s free. You download it and you run it. It’s as simple as that.
第一次使用时它的界面是这样的
This is what it’s going to look like when you first bring it up,
这是启动画面
this splash screen here.
随着学期的进行 这里将充满你所做的各种项目
As the quarter goes on, this will fill up with all the projects that you’re doing.
用过 Xcode 的人应该会很习惯
You’re probably used to that if you know Xcode.
今天我们要创建一个新项目
And what we’re going to do today is create a new project.
你可以到源控制中查看已有项目
You can either check an existing project out of source control
你也可以创建新的
or you can create a new one.
我们要创建新的
And so we’re going to create a new one.
创建新项目时 它会尝试给我们一点帮助
So when we create a new one, it wants to give us a little bit of help
它会给我们提供不同应用的模板
by offering to create a template for different kinds of applications
比如 openGL 游戏
like an openGL game.
它会为你创建某种框架
Okay. It will create some framework for that for you.
Master-Detail 应用
Master detail applications,
这是我们这学期晚些时候要做的
something we’re going to do later in the quarter,
只是我们会自己写代码
although we’re going to build all the code ourselves;
我们不会用这个模板
we’re not going to use this template.
这里的单视图应用就是一单个 MVC
And this single view application one right here is basically a single MVC,
课上我们的所有应用都将由此开始
which is how we’re going it start all of our applications in this classroom –
首先是单个 MVC 之后再添加更多 MVC
with a single MVC. Then we’re going to add more MVCs and build up.
这是基本的单 MVC app
So this is your basic single MVC app.
点击这个
So I’m going to click that.
这里它会要求一些相关信息
And here it’s going to ask for some information about it
例如 你想给该 app 起什么名
like what do you want to call this app?
这是一个扑克牌匹配游戏 我打算叫它 Machismo
This is a card matching game I have decided to call Machismo.
这是我们 app 的名称 起个有趣的名字
So that’s going to be the name of our app just for fun.
组织名可以任选
And organization name can be anything you want.
它会显示在你创建的所有类的头文件之中
It’s going to appear in the headers of all the classes that you create.
我这里写斯坦福大学
So I make mine be Stanford University.
你们也可以写 Bob’s Game House 什么都行
You can make yours be Bob’s Game House or whatever.
这个标识符对你需要是唯一的
This identifier should be unique to you.
我的是 edu.Stanford.cs193p.instructor
So I have edu.Stanford.cs193p.instructor.
你的可以是 edu.Stanford.cs193p. 你的 SUNet ID
You might have edu.Stanford.cs193p dot your SUNet ID.
这肯定是独一无二的
That will be completely unique.
这些反的 DNS 能给出很好的唯一名称
These reverse DNS is a really good way to create a unique name.
它还会为这个 app 创建一个唯一名称
And it’s going to create a unique name for this app
通过将这个和名称结合
by combining this with the names.
如这里的包标识符
So you can see it’s done that here, this bundle identifier.
然后这个类前缀
And then this class prefix –
这一模板将为我们创建一个视图和一个控制器
this template is going to create a view and a controller for us.
这里说的是 你希望你的控制器类名为什么
And this is saying, “What do you want the name of your controller class to be?”
默认情况下 它会被叫作 ViewController
By default it’s going to be called “view controller,” okay?
但如果这里你键入诸如 CardGame
But if you type something here like “card game,” now
它就会叫作 CardGameViewController
it’s going to be called “card game view controller,”
这个名字对我们更好
which is a little better name for us.
它为你创建这个控制器时 会加上这个前缀
So that’s just the prefix it’s going to put on the name
of your controller that it creates for you.
最后这里我们可以让创建的 app
And then finally here we can create an app here just
只适用于 iPad 只适用于 iPhone
for iPad, or just for iPhone,
或能够运行在两个平台上的通用 app
or a universal app that will run on both platforms.
创建通用 app 时 UI 仍然需要单独设计
Now, when you create a universal app, you still have to design your UI’s separately
因为屏幕规则更多时 你需要设计不同的 UI
because if you have more screen rules, you’re just going to design a different UI.
iPad 不只是一个大 iPhone
iPad is not just a big iPhone.
有更多屏幕空间时 你可以做更多事情
You can do a lot more stuff if you have more screen real estate.
但你仍然可以让很多 MVC 共享
But you still might have a lot of your MVC’s shared, right,
因为 iPad 中在 MVC 中可能有一些小的子区域
because that iPad might have little subareas that are in MVC
同 iPhone 完全相同 或非常非常相似
that are exactly the same as on an iPhone or very, very similar.
iOS7 中完全支持让创建的 app 同时针对两大平台
So totally supported in iOS 7 to build apps that target both platforms
也有很棒的工具让你能单独创建两个 UI
and has great tools for letting you build your two UI’s separately
并共享下面的所有 MVC
and share all the MVCs underneath.
这里我们只针对 iPhone 编程
We’re going to do iPhone only here just
因为这样屏幕更小 而我只有这么大的屏幕空间
because it keeps the screen small and I only have so much real estate here.
[学生提问 声音不清]
[Inaudible]
Paul Hegarty：问题是 我在 iPad 上能否
> Paul Hegarty: Yeah. So the question is: If I’m on my iPad
运行只针对 iPhone 的 app 能
and I run an app that’s iPhone only, yes,
这里可以说有一个仿真模式
there’s an emulation mode essentially that will kind
将一个大的 iPhone 状东西放到 iPad 屏幕上
of make a big iPhone-shaped thing on the iPad screen.
这里我选 iPhone
So we’re going to do iPhone here.
然后点下一步
So that’s it. I’m going to hit next.
下一步它想知道 “你要把这个项目放在哪”
Next it wants to know, “Where are you going it put this project?”
我强烈推荐放在主目录中
I strongly recommend putting it in your home directory –
一个叫作 developer(开发者) 的目录内
in a directory called “developer” in your home directory.
除非你要使用不同的类
Unless maybe we’re working on different class.
也许你有 cs193p 在主目录下 然后其它类
Maybe you have the CS 193P in your home directory and then other class.
总之 把它放到主目录中
But bottom line: Put it in your home directory;
不要放到根或类似的地方
do not put it, like, in root or somewhere like that.
这在原来导致过问题
That has in the past caused problems.
放在这里很好 这是我的主目录 这是 cs193p
But a great place to put it here. This is my home directory, CS 193P there.
主目录 developer
I see home directory, developer.
我将把它放到这里 这里还没有任何项目
This is where I’m going to put it. I don’t have any projects yet.
这下面有一个小内容 叫源控制 我会讲到这个
This little thing down here, source control, we will be talking about that.
它很好地整合到了 Xcode 中
It’s really nicely integrated into Xcode,
不过今天我不打算讲
but we’re not going to talk about it today.
这个不选
So leave that unclicked.
这是我们的新项目
And so here’s our new project.
它会显示这个屏幕
You can see it shows us this screen,
可以通过点上面这个来得到
which you get to by clicking on this very top thing up here.
这是我们的项目设置
So this is kind of like our project settings.
这里有很多设置
And there’s a whole bunch of settings here.
这学期我会讲到所有这些
We’ll be talk being all this stuff as the quarter goes on.
但今天我不打算讲 因为我要将焦点集中在 MVC 上
But today we’re not going to talk about any of it because we want to focus on our MVC.
我们的 MVC 中 这里这个 Main.storyboard 是我们的视图
And our MVC, this right here, main.storyboard, is our view.
这是 MVC 中的视图
That’s our view of our MVC.
然后这里有 CardGameViewController.m 和.h
And then you see this card game view controller M and H?
这是我们的控制器
That’s our controller.
这里没有模型
There’s no model here.
模型将是那四个类
Your model is going to be those four classes –
Deck Card PlayingCard PlayingCardDeck
deck, card, playing card, playing card deck –
这将是你的模型
that’s going to be your model.
你需要输入这些
So you’ll have to enter that in.
最后我会展示如何做到
I’ll show you at the end how to do that.
这里的 CardGameAppDelegate.h 和.m
This little thing here, card game app delegate dot H and M,
这个我在讲多任务处理这些时会简要讲到
we’ll talk about that briefly, especially when we start talking about things like multitasking.
这里我不想看到它们
But I like to just move those out of the way.
我通常把它们放到支持文件文件夹中
So I often put them down here in this supporting files folder.
顺便说下 文件可以直接拖动 拖到哪都行
And you can just pick up any file, by the way, and move them anywhere you want
这是为了屏幕上更简洁
here to kind of clean up your view.
这里于是就只显示有视图和控制器了
So here I’ve got my view and my controller only showing here.
我们直接到视图 看它是怎样的
So let’s go straight to the view and see what that looks like.
这是我的视图 一个空 iPhone5 大小的空间
So here’s my view. It’s a blank iPhone 5 sized, right?
一个又高又窄的视图
A tall and thin view.
而且它是空的 什么都没有 空白一片
And it’s blank. Nothing new. It’s white.
顺便说下 这里用来点击文件的地方
This area on the left, by the way, where we clicked on these files,
叫作导航栏
that’s called the “navigator.”
你不仅可以浏览所有文件
And you can not only navigate all your files here,
你还可以浏览断点
but you can navigate your break points,
创建问题 类层次结构
and build problems, and your class hierarchies.
这些都在这上面
All that stuff up here.
大多数人用过 Xcode 应该都知道这些
So again, most of you know Xcode, so you probably know most of this stuff.
我们在这学期的过程中会不断演示
We’ll be demoing all this as the quarter goes on.
而这块区域叫作”工具区”
And this area over here is called the “utilities area.”
这里会显示中间这里的细节情况
And this is where you basically find out detail about what’s going on here.
例如属性 尺寸 连接检查器
So inspectors for attributes, and dimensions, and connections,
这些都在这里
and things like that go here.
而且这里还可以拖出这些东西
And this is also where you can drag out the things
用于构建你的用户界面
that you’re going to use to build your user interface
因为我们将要完全图形化地创建视图
because we’re going to build our view entirely graphically.
我们大多数时候会写代码来创建视图
We’re not going to write code, for the most part, to build our view.
随着学期进行 我们会更多地学到如何写代码来创建视图
As the quarter goes on, we’ll learn a little more about how to build our view in code,
但最开始 我们将只使用图形化操作来创建视图
but we’re going to start out just purely doing our view by graphically
将事物拖入 连起
dragging things out and wiring them up.
然后我们再在控制器中写代码
And we’ll put our code in our controller.
这两个边栏可以通过这两个按钮来隐藏和显示
This two sides can be hidden and shown with these two buttons.
看到了吗 你可以隐藏它们
See? You can hide those.
这个按钮也可以点 显示出的这个区域
This might appear also, this area right here, this little button down here.
叫作”文档大纲”
This is called the “document outline.”
这也很有用
This is really handy dandy.
但我今天不打算讲
But again, we’re not going it talk about that today.
一次我只能讲那么多
We can only talk about so much at once.
文档大纲
The document outline.
它会将视图中所有对象实例以大纲形式展示出来
This just shows you all the instances of objects in your view in a common outline form.
这样你就能够很轻松地弄清它们之间的相互关系
So you can really easily find them and their relationships to each other.
另外你还可以说 我不想要 iPhone5 的屏幕大小
The other thing you can do is I don’t want this iPhone 5 sized
因为我的屏幕没有这么大 这里我是为了配合投影仪
thing because my screen is low resolution here so it works on the projector.
这时可以点这个按钮
So I’m going to click this little button down here,
这可以将屏幕缩小到 iPhone4 或 4S 的大小
which reduces me down to iPhone 4 size. Or iPhone 4S.
而非又高又窄
Not tall and thin.
你可以点这个来回切换
But you can click back and forth and move them back forth.
我这里只是想让它更好地匹配投影仪大小
And I’m just trying to make everything fit on screen here.
好 让我们开始真正构建视图
Okay. So let’s just dive right into building our view here.
今天我们的视图将是一张上面写有梅花 A 的纸牌
What our view is going to be today is a single card with an ace of clubs written on it.
就这些了
That’s going to be it.
而且我能点击纸牌
And I’m going to be able to click on the card
它会翻过来 显示背面
and it will flip over, show the back of the card,
再点击 它会翻回来 显示正面的梅花 A
and then click on it again, it will flip back to show me the ace of club again –
来回来回
back and forth, back and forth.
而你们的作业是
And your homework is going to be to make it
当纸牌翻转时 显示的不是梅花 A
so when the card flips up it doesn’t show the ace of clubs,
而是从牌堆中随机抽取的牌
it shows a random card drawn from the deck.
这是周一要交的作业的全部内容
That’s going to be your entire homework that’s due on Monday.
好 我们来做这个 很简单
Okay. So let’s do this. Really simple.
我们到这里 这个对象库
We go to this area right here, this object library.
也就是这里第三个按钮 显示对象库
That’s the third button over here, show object library.
对象都在这里
And this is where all our objects are.
只看这里 你还看不到这些对象
If you look in here and you don’t see these objects,
你要点击视图
it might be worth clicking on your view.
有时 Xcode 想知道目的地在哪
Sometimes Xcode wants to know what the destination is
你要把东西拖放到哪
that you’re going to be dragging things into.
点击之后 你会看到这些东西
So if you click on it, then you’ll see these things.
我们将抓取这里的一个按钮
And we’re just going to grab one of these buttons right here.
我选取这个按钮 并拖出
So I’m going to pick this button up and drag it out.
注意到 当我拖出它时
And notice, as I drag it out,
这些蓝色的参考线会显示出来
these little blue lines appear — these guidelines.
这些参考线非常重要
Okay. These guidelines are super important.
它们除了方便
They seem just like a convenience
帮你将对象放到中间或右下角这些地方以外
for helping you put it right in the middle or right in the right-hand corner.
它们的重要性还体现在 帮你确保
And they are, but they’re really important for making sure
视图中的所有东西都相隔标准距离
that all the things in your view are kind of, like, standard space apart.
并在边缘处对齐
And lined up against edges.
当用户从一个 app 到另一个时
So that as the users go from one app to another,
事物将以可预测的距离分开 一切都会保持一致
things will all be separated by predictable spaces and everything will be consistent.
这很重要
It’s really important.
这里还有一个机制 可以看到这里有个开关
And there’s a mechanism — you can see this switch right here,
使用自动布局 这是在 iOS6 中引入的
use auto layout, which was introduced in iOS 6
在 iOS7 中 特别是 Xcode 中得到了大幅提升
and vastly improved in iOS 7, especially in Xcode –
这使得 当你的用户界面改变大小时
that allows when your user interface changes size,
例如从 iPhone4 到 iPhone5
like it goes from being an iPhone 4 to an iPhone 5,
或者从竖直旋转为水平
or it rotates from being vertical to being horizontal,
或是在 iPad 上 有更大空间
or it’s on an iPad in a bigger space.
这会让所有按钮等元件合理地移动到新位置
For all the buttons and everything to kind of move to a new position that makes sense
至少大多数移到合理位置
or at least most of them, right?
还有一些 你可能需要手工移动
And then maybe you might have to move a few of them by hand,
取决于具体情况
depending on what’s going on. But
但基本上是自动布局
it mostly automatically lays it out.
这很重要
And this is really important
因为设备将不断变换大小
because I’m sure devices will continue to be differing sizes
每年都会有新设备出来
as new, you know, devices come out over the years.
所以 使用自动布局很重要
So doing auto layout is important,
而这些蓝色参考线对于自动布局是第一重要的东西
and these blue guidelines are the number one most important thing for auto layout.
我会详细讲解自动布局 它有很多内容
We’re going to cover auto layout in detail, and there’s a lot to it.
下面所有这些按钮都与自动布局有关
All these buttons down here have to do with auto layout.
得到这些蓝色参考线 确保元件所放位置
But getting those blue guidelines, making sure you drop things
至少能够显示出一条蓝色参考线 非常重要
with at least one blue guideline somewhere is really important
这能让你的元件在 UI 自动布局时找到正确的位置
to kind get you going down the right path with the properly auto laid out UI.
这里有个按钮
So we have this button here.
当然 我们可以到这里
But before — and of course, we can go over here
这里是属性检查器 点击它
to this is the attributes inspector and click on it.
这里有各种属性
And we’ll see all kinds of attributes.
我可以隐藏这个 这里有该按钮各式各样的属性
In fact, if I hide this, tons and tons of attributes for this button.
不只是按钮本身
Not just the button itself,
它的父类也有属性
but actually its superclass has attributes.
Control 是它的父类
Control is its superclass,
然后 View 是 Control 的父类 它也有属性
and then view is control’s superclass and it has attributes.
这是一个面向对象的检查器
Okay. So this is an object-oriented inspector
它会显示出继承层次下的所有属性
that will show all the attributes of all the things through the inheritance hierarchy.
这里我们所做的 实际上是编辑一个按钮的实例
And what’s happening here is we’re actually editing an instance of a button here.
我们不是… 我知道
So we are not — and I know
某些系统中 你布局按钮 设定大小 设定属性
in some systems you layout the button, you set the size, and you set the attributes.
然后在幕后
And then, you know, behind the scenes a bunch
一堆代码会生成出来 创建按钮
of code is being generated to create the button.
这里不是这样
That’s not what we’re doing here.
我们是在编辑活动对象
We’re actually editing live objects.
它们就像是速冻咖啡粉末
They’re essentially going to be freeze dried.
app 运行就像加水 它们会被注入生命
And then when your app runs, add water, they come to life, okay,
它们的属性会被设置 它们的大小和位置
with their attributes set, and all their sizes and positions,
以及所有的自动布局信息都在对象中
and all their auto layout information in the object.
这有些不同于其它系统中你们所习惯的情况
So it’s a little different than you might be used to in some other systems.
无论如何 在我们编辑这个按钮的属性前
So anyway, before we edit the attributes of this button,
我们先来换个背景 因为这是一个扑克牌游戏
though, let’s change our background because this is a card game.
而大多数扑克牌游戏都是绿色绒布 对吧
And most card games are on, like, green felt, right?
让我们把背景换得更像绿色绒布
So let’s make our background be more like a green felt.
我将点击背景
So I’m just going to click on the background,
也就是这个 View 可以看到它的属性
which is this view right here, and you can see its properties.
我将改变这个背景属性
So I’m going to change a couple — or just one of its properties — which is the background.
这里背景还是白色
You see this background white color right here?
点击这里 这里有一些最近使用过的颜色
So if I click on this, I have some recently used colors.
我有所有这些黑白颜色
I have all these kind of black and white colors.
这里还有其它颜色
And I also have other.
点其它会出现这些蜡笔
And I bring up other, brings up the crayons.
还有其它选择颜色的方式 不过我喜欢蜡笔
It also brings up other ways to choose colors, but I like the crayons.
我的蜡笔呢
And so where are my crayons?
这里
There they are.
我们来选一种绿色 青苔色是很好的绿色
So let’s pick a green, like, moss is a good green.
苜蓿色 我更喜欢青苔色
Clover. I kind of like moss better.
这是纸牌游戏的背景
So that’s kind of a card game background.
这就行了 我们设置好了 View 的背景颜色
And that’s it. So we’ve set the background color of our views.
所有的属性设置都和这类似
And all the attribute setting is just like this:
设置好了就可以不用管了
You just set it and forget it.
我们回到按钮和它的属性
So let’s go back to the button and its properties.
按钮我希望它像一张纸牌
Okay. The button I want to look like a card.
iOS7 中的按钮比较像网页中的超链接
Well, a button in iOS 7 basically looks a lot like a hyperlink on a web page,
就像这个按钮所做的 这个蓝色按钮
just like that button does right there. That blue button.
这不是我们想要的
That’s not really appropriate for what we want.
我们希望它是一张牌 有圆角矩形边框和白色背景
We want it to look like a card with a little rounded rect and a white background, right?
我希望纸牌背面都一样
And I want the back of the card to look the same
而且具有某种图样设计
but have some kind of design on it or something like that.
所以 我将为我的按钮设置一个背景图
So the way I’m going to do that is I’m going to set a background image for my button.
一个圆角矩形的背景图
A background image that’s like a rounded rect.
这里我们先简单讲一下
So let’s take a little aside here and talk about:
如何将图像置入到 app 中
How do we get images into our app?
app 中经常会用到图像
Okay. We want to use images in our app; it’s very common to want to use images
手机程序一般都是图形程序
in a graphical application like on a phone.
那如何做到呢
So how do you do it?
答案是 你可以到下面这个地方 它叫作
And the answer is you go down here to this place called the
图像资源库 Images.xcassets
”image asset library” — images.xc assets
xcassets 也就是 Xcode 资源
or Xcode assets.
可以看到这里已经有一些图标槽位存在
And you can see there’s already a couple of slots for icons here.
你可以在这里设置 app 图标
They’re not set, but this is the app icon.
你还可以设置一个启动画面
And also you can have a launch image that will appear instantly
程序启动后需要初始化 启动画面会立刻显示
when someone launches your app. And then as you’re initializing,
初始化后再才显示出实际的 UI
having behind the launch image, and then it will show you are actual UI.
这是一个快速的启动画面
So it’s kind of quick launch image.
周一我会讲到这个
And we’ll talk about this on Monday.
这里我们将为 Machismo 设置背景
We’ll set the app background for Machismo here.
我将拖入其它图像
But I’m going to actually drag in some other image.
这里我有一些图像
So I have some images here.
例如 这里我有这个斯坦福的 logo
And for example, I’ve got this Stanford logo right here.
我将把这个斯坦福的 logo 拖入
So I’m going to drag that Stanford logo in
因为我要用它
because I want to use it.
把它拖到这里就行了
And that’s it; you just drag it in here.
这是斯坦福 logo
It says Stanford.
但注意到 这里有很奇怪的 1x 和 2x
But notice that it kind of has this weird thing here, this 1X and 2X.
看到了吗 这是因为 iOS 中你们要用到的每张图像
You see that? And that’s because every image that you’re going to use in iOS
需要有一个普通分辨率版本
wants to have a normal resolution version that’s going
用于 iPhone4 这样的非视网膜屏
to be used like on the iPhone 4 — nonretina displays basically.
而 2x 是两倍高分辨率版本 用于视网膜屏
And then a 2X, twice as high resolution — one that will be used on retina.
系统会自动选择正确的图像 取决于运行于什么设备
And it will automatically pick the right one, depending on what you’re running on.
你不需要做任何事
You don’t have to do anything about it.
但你需要提供这些高清版本
But you do want to provide these higher res ones.
这些高清版本并不一定要是原来一样的图像
And these higher res ones aren’t just necessarily the same exact image,
只是分辨率更高一些
just, you know, made more high resolution.
它们可以不同
They might allow you to do –
例如这里 我有一个带树的斯坦福 logo
for example, here I’ve got a Stanford logo with the little tree.
看到树了吗
See? See the tree in there?
也许这里由于分辨率太低 树不是很好看
So maybe this is too low resolution to really get a good-looking tree.
但在高分辨率下我可以加个树 所以我加了
But I can get the tree in at a higher resolution, so I put it in there.
两个图像不一样的情况并不常见
So it’s not that common that the two ones would be actually
但它们确实可以不同
different-looking but they could be.
这肯定是允许的
Certainly allowed they could be.
我也不想把这个叫斯坦福
I also don’t want to really call this “Stanford.”
我将把这用作纸牌的背面
I’m going to use this as my backup card.
纸牌背面我将不使用某种花纹
Instead of having, you know, some kind of design,
而使用斯坦福的 logo
I’m going to have the Stanford logo be the back of my card.
纸牌翻过来时 我会看到背面的斯坦福 logo
When my card’s flipped down and I see the back, I’m going to see the Stanford logo.
所以我将给它取名为 cardback
So I’m going to call this “card back.”
其实叫什么都行
I can call it anything I want.
正面我也有个图像
I also have things for the front here.
这个
This one right here.
这是带有圆角的空纸牌
This is blank card with a rounded corner.
这里
There it is.
哦 你们看不到
You can’t see it.
因为这是白色纸牌 所以你们看不到
Because it’s a white card so you can’t see it.
但我将使用它 取名为 cardfront
But I’m going to use that. I’m going to call this “card front.”
我还将有一个高清版的
And I’m also going to have a high-res version of that as well.
好 这很不错
Okay. So that’s good.
它只能显示成这样
So as much as we can see of it.
以上一些图像
Okay. So now I got some images.
下面我将把它们用到我的视图中
And now I want to use them in my view.
我将设置纸牌 来使用这个
I kind of want to set this card to use this.
程序运行时 我希望纸牌最开始是正面朝上
So I’m going to start with my card here being face up when it runs.
app 运行时 纸牌最开始是正面朝上
When my app runs, the card’s going to start face up.
在作业 app 中 你们需要让它正面朝下
In your app when you get your homework you’re probably going to want to start it facedown.
原因在于 我的 app 只显示一张牌
The reason for that is my app only shows one card:
梅花 A
Ace of clubs.
所以最开始梅花 A 朝上没有关系
So it’s fine if it comes up with ace of clubs.
但你们显然不希望一开始就是梅花 A
But you don’t want your card to come up ace of clubs for sure.
而且代码上 你们也需要更多工作
And it might be a little more work for you coding-wise
才能初始化它 得到随机的牌
to initialize it to come up with some random card.
所以你们应该让它正面朝下 这会更容易一些
So you’ll just have it come up facedown. Make it a lot easier on you.
这如何设置呢
So how do we set that?
很简单
Really simple.
这里有已选定的按钮
I’ve got the button selected here.
这是它的属性
Here’s its properties.
一个属性是它的背景图像
One of its properties is its background image.
我要点击这里 可以看到
So I’m just going to click here, and you can see
资源库中的所有图像都在这里
that all images that are in my assets library will be here.
有很多的话 你可以键入字符 它会自行匹配
And if there was a really lot of them, you can type and it will match it.
我将把它设为 cardfront
So I’m going to make it be the card front.
这就设为了正面 但圆角矩形在哪
So it made it the card front, but I don’t see — where’s the rounded rect?
我看不到圆角矩形 这是因为它太小了
I can’t see the rounded rect. And that’s because it’s too small
圆角看不大清楚
to see the rounded corners very well here.
这里你可以将它拉大一些
So you can just take this thing and resize it.
我希望让它…
And I’m going to make it –
这里我希望比例是 2:3 我将使用 64×96
I want it to be about two to three ratio. So I’m going to make it 64 by 96.
这是一个很好的尺寸 我调整了它的大小
I know this happens to be a very good size, and I’ve resized it.
这时就可以看到圆角了
And now you can see the little rounded corners.
看到了吗 这就是我刚才拖入的图像
You see? So this is that image I dragged in
上面写有 Button
with button written on top of it.
我还可以将它移动一下
And of course, I moved it a little so I can put it back
放到蓝色参考线的中间
in the middle using my blue guidelines, right?
当然 我不希望纸牌上写有 Button
And of course, I don’t want my card to say “button” it;
我希望这里是梅花 A 我可以双击它
I want the ace of clubs on here. So I’m going to just double-click on it.
我也可以在这上面编辑
I could also edit that up here.
看到了吗 这里写的是 Button
You see right here where it says “button”?
点击这里
Click it here.
我将直接双击它
I’m just going to double-click directly on it.
我将输入 A
I’m going to type “ace.”
如何输入梅花 有人知道吗
And how do I type clubs, anyone know?
Alt+ 什么 我喜欢这样做
Alt something or other. I like to do this way.
到编辑菜单 选特殊字符 弹出这个窗口
I go to edit menu, special characters, get this magic thing.
看过这个吗 很酷吧
You ever seen this, kind of cool?
双击 找到梅花 然后双击
Just double-click — find the clubs and double-click.
好 这就是我的梅花 A 了
All right. So there’s my ace of clubs.
不过这也不是很好
Now but, you know, that’s not quite right, either.
我不喜欢这个蓝 A 我希望 A 是黑色的
I don’t really like that blue A. I really want the A to be black.
而且它可以更大一些 这里还有更大空间
And it could be a little bigger. There’s more room for it.
我可以到这里 来改变字体
So I can go over here, for example, and change the font.
我可以点这个 让它更大
I can change it by clicking this little thing to make it bigger,
我也可以点击这个 T 设置它为哪一种字体
or I can actually click on this T and even set which font it is.
iOS7 中很重要的一点是排版
One thing that’s really important in iOS 7 is the typography.
选择正确的文本样式在 iOS7 中非常非常重要
Picking the right text styles is really, really important in iOS 7.
这里我不打算细讲
And we’re not going to really talk about it here;
我将使用系统字体
we’re just going to use the system font.
不过以后课上我会讲到
But that’s something we’ll talk about in lecture,
确保正确地方使用了正确字体
is making sure you pick the right fonts in the right places
才能让 UI 看起来更漂亮
to make the UI look really nice.
这里我可以改变字符大小 也许 24 点就差不多了
I can change the size here, maybe 24 point or something like that.
这就行了
That will still fit.
然后我不要蓝色 点这里换字符颜色
And then I don’t want this blue, so that’s this text color.
我们要把这个换成黑色
So let’s go ahead and make that black.
好 这样牌就弄成了我想要的样子
All right. So I got the card looking the way I want.
这很好
That’s good.
顺便说下 我们设置的所有这些属性
All these properties that we’re setting, by the way,
Button 下面可以看到这个状态配置
if you look at button, you see this state config right here?
这是默认 我们可以设置所有不同状态
Default? We can actually set all these things differently
包括按钮的高亮状态 或选择状态 或禁用状态
for the highlighted state of the button, or a selected state, or disabled state.
不过这里我们设置的是默认
But we’re setting these as the default.
所有按钮都总会显示出默认状态
So all our buttons always going to be displaying the default state.
按钮非常强大
So buttons are pretty powerful.
你可以让它们在高亮或别的状态中有所不同
You can have them look different as they highlight or whatever,
但我们这里用到的将是
but we’re going to be working all in what’s called the
”正常”或”默认”状态下的按钮
”normal” or “default” state of the button.
看代码时你们会看到这个
You’ll see that when we get to the code.
我们现在就可以运行这个了
So we can actually run this right now.
运行
So running.
你们大多数人用过 Xcode
You’ve all — most, again, done Xcode.
知道如何运行 也就是这个小的播放按钮
You know how to run. It’s this little play button.
下拉列表里还有
You can actually hold it down,
测试和分析等其它这些东西
and there’s other things you can do like test and analyze.
这里我们要运行
But we’re just going to run.
点运行 它会在模拟器中运行
So I click run, and it’s going to run this in a simulator.
这就是了
And here it is.
可以看到 模拟器很大 我的屏幕放不下
And you can see that the simulator’s so big it doesn’t even fit on my screen.
所以我需要滚动
So I kind of have to scroll around in it.
点击它 它什么都做不了
And when I click it, it doesn’t do anything.
这个不好
So that’s not good.
因为控制器中我还没有加入任何代码
Because I haven’t put any code in my controller
来对点击作出响应
to respond to that thing being touched.
这将是我们下面的工作
So that’s what we’re going to do next.
回到这里来 停止
So let’s go back here and stop.
那么 怎么做到呢
So how do we do that?
这个做起来会非常有趣
Well, it’s pretty interesting how we do that, actually.
我这里留一些空间出来
I’m going to make some more space here.
我们需要把它同控制器联系起来
And what we need to do is connect up to our controller.
做法是对照视图 并排加入控制器代码
And we do that by putting our controller’s code side by side with our view.
我将点击这个小按钮
So I’m going to click this little button right here,
这个按钮图标 表示并排显示
this button icon, and that puts side by side.
默认情况下 如果视图在左边
And by default if you have a view up here on the left,
控制器代码会显示在右边
it’s going to put that controller’s code on the right.
我们可以移动这个 给代码腾出更大空间
And you can move this to get more space for the code if you want.
这里还可以在处理公共内容的头文件
You can also switch between the header if you want to do public stuff
和实现之间来回切换
or the implementation.
这很棒
So that’s good.
这段代码是视图控制器生命周期的部分
Now, this code right here is part of the view controller lifecycle,
我们会在两三周后谈到
which we’re going to talk about in two or three weeks.
不过今天我不打算讲它 让我把它删掉
But today we’re not going to talk about it. So we can just get rid of it.
今天我只想说
And let’s just start by saying,
这个按钮被触碰到时 我们希望它翻个面
”When this button gets touched, we want it to flip over.”
我们需要将视图和控制器连接起来
So we need to make a connection between our view and the controller.
我们会将目标挂出去 然后将箭发射
And we’re going to do that thing where we hang the target out and shoot the arrow.
这是目标 动作
Called “target action.”
这会有些怪异
And this is going to be kind of whacky.
看到这个时 你可能都不敢相信自己的眼睛
You’re probably not even going to believe this when you see it.
做法是按住 Control 键
The way to do this is you hold down the control key.
我按住 Control 键 然后拖一条线
So I’m holding down the control key, and I’m dragging a line
从视图直接拖到代码中
from the view directly into our code.
让后松手
And I let go.
然后它说 哦 你想在视图和控制器之间建立连接 对吧
And it says, “Oh, you want a connection between your view and your controller, do you?
这就是我需要知道的
Here’s what I need to know.”
它问我们 你希望给这个连接取名叫什么
So it’s asking us, “What you do you want to call this connection?”
这将是方法名
So this is going to be the name of the method.
它会创建一个在按钮被触碰到时调用的方法
It’s actually going to create a method here that gets called when the button gets touched.
这里我给它取名叫 touchCardButton(触摸纸牌按钮)
I’m going to call it “touch card button.”
这个名字不错
That’s a good name.
这里它问的是 你希望参数类型是什么
Here it’s saying, “What you do you want the type of the argument to be?”
以后我会讲到
We’ll talk about this later,
不过这里 我们显然希望参数是
but for now we obviously want the argument to be
发送给我们这个动作的按钮
the button that is sending us this action.
我们能够回头告诉它翻过来 这会很好
Which is going to be nice because then we’re going
to talk back to it and tell it to flip itself over.
这里我们还可以设置
There’s other things we can set here like:
你想在哪一类事件下发送这个动作
What kind of event do you want to send this action?
你可以设置为无参数
And you can actually set it so there’s no argument,
它会发送 touchCardButton 不带参数
it just sends touch card button with no arguments.
但这里我们希望 Sender 这一参数
But here we want it to have the argument of the sender,
即发送这一消息的按钮
the button sending this message.
你还可以发送触摸事件
You can even send the touch event along,
但我们几乎从不这样做 使用率小于 0.1%
but we almost never do that — a tenth of a percent of the time.
这里选 Sender
So here I’m going to have the sender.
我点击连接时 它会创建一个新方法
So when I click connect, it creates a new method.
这一方法同这一按钮接通起来
And that method is wired up to that button.
看到这个圆圈了吗
In fact, you see this little round circle?
鼠标放到上面 它就会告诉你 它连接到的是什么
If I mouse over it, it will show you that’s what it’s connected to.
这是一个非常普通的方法
So this is just some pretty normal-looking method right here.
返回类型 IBAction 这实际上是 typedef void
The return type, IB action, that’s actually typedef void.
这个方法实际返回 void
This method actually returns void.
Xcode 之所以加上 IBAction
The reason that Xcode puts IB action there
将 IBAction 类型定义到 void 只是为了便于分辨
and typedef’s IB action to void, it’s just so that it can tell
哪个方法是目标动作
which methods are target action
于是它可以做这样的事情
so that it can do stuff like this.
鼠标悬停
The mouse over.
但编译器会忽略它
But the compiler ignores it.
编译器会把它看作 void 因为它被类型定义为 void
The compiler sees it as void because it’s typedef to void.
IBAction 完全是为 Xcode 考虑
It’s purely an Xcode thing to this IB action thing.
然后这个方法有一个参数 也就是 sender
And then you can see this method has one argument, which is the sender.
这是发送我们这一消息的按钮
That’s the button sending us this message.
每次按钮被触摸时 它都会发送这一消息
And it’s going to send this message every time a touch goes up inside the button.
事件是触摸按钮
Touch up inside, right? That was the event.
这时它会发送这一消息
So that’s when it’s going to send this message.
这很完美 这就是我们要的
So that’s perfect. That’s what we want.
每次发生这个时 我们想要做什么
So every time this happens, what do we want to do?
我们希望将纸牌翻过来
Well, we want to flip the card over.
我们首先来考虑如何翻到反面
Okay. So let’s start by just flipping it over to the back.
为此 我们将创建一个局部变量
And the way we’re going to do that is we’re going to create a local variable
叫 cardImage(纸牌图像)
called “card image.”
可以看到 它正为我提供键入帮助 这里会有很多帮助
Okay. And you noticed it was trying to help me type there,
and you’re going to see a lot of helping here.
UIImage 是 iOS 中的另一个类 就像 UIButton 一样
And UI image is another class in iOS, okay, just like UI button is a class.
UIImage 顾名思义 是用来存储图像的
UI image is the class, as you can imagine, stores an image.
可以是 JPEG 图像 可以是 GIF 动画
Could be a JPEG image, could be an animated GIF,
可以是 TIFF 图像 这些都行
it could be a TIFF image, whatever.
这是一种很强大的容纳图像的类
So it’s very powerful image holding class.
它有一个类方法 叫 imageNamed(图像名叫)
And it has a class method called “image named,”
你给它一个字符串 例如 cardfront 或 cardback
and you give it a string like card front or card back, right?
它会到资源库并给出一个分辨率正确的图像
And it will look in the assets library and give an image of the right resolution,
实际上 它会给你两种分辨率的图像
depending on whether it’s going to be go on –
actually, it will give you an image with both resolutions.
然后取决于是否在视网膜屏上显示
And then depending on where you display it, it will, you know,
它会为你选出正确分辨率的图像
pick the right resolution, whether it’s on a retina or not.
这很酷 我们得到了图像
So that’s cool. We got the image.
然后我们要告诉按钮把这个
So now we’re just going to tell the button to set this
设置为背景图像
as its background image
替换现在它上面的图像
instead of whatever’s on it right now.
要同按钮通信 我们用 [sender
So to talk to the button, we do open square bracket sender.
sender 也就是发送这一消息的按钮
Right? You see that the sender is the button sending us this message.
设置背景 这里键入 setBackground…
Set. Okay, I’m going to start typing set background.
注意在我键入的过程中 Xcode 会为我提供一些建议
And you see as I start to type, Xcode is suggesting to me what I might want.
它知道 sender 是一个 UIButton
Now, it knows that the sender’s a UI button,
所以它这里只会给我推荐以 setB 开头的按钮方法
so it’s only suggesting button methods here that start with set B –
setBackgroundColor setBackgroundImage
set background color, set background image,
和 setBounds
and set bounds.
注意下方还有一些帮助信息
Notice I’m also getting some help at the bottom.
很酷吧
See, isn’t that cool?
有一两行的简短帮助
A little one or two lines of help?
我还可以点这个链接
And I could click on this link
这会让我看到说明文档
and it would take me to the documentation.
由于时间原因 我这里就不点了
We’re not going to do that for time reasons.
不过我可以选择一个 它会写出这一个
But I can also just click one and it picks that one
并立刻选择第一个参数
and immediately selects the first argument.
我可以填入这个
So I can take that.
我要这样做
So I’ll do that.
cardImage
Card image.
注意到 当我键入 ca 时 这里给出了很多东西
And notice here when I type CA, there’s a lot of things
所有 ca 开头的都在这里
that start with CA that could go there.
但 Xcode 很聪明
But Xcode’s pretty smart.
它知道局部变量更可能是你要的
It knows that a local variable is much more likely what you want here
相比其它这些 ca 开头的函数
than all these other CA — functions that start with CA.
于是它自动给我选了这个
So it automatically selects that for me.
如果我按 Tab 键
And if I hit tab, by the way,
它会自动给我补全 Tab 用于补全
it’s going to basically escape complete it. Tab, complete it.
再点一下 Tab 它会跳到这里
And if I hit another tab, it goes over here.
这里 forState 也就是我刚才讲过的内容
This little forState thing is just what I was talking about where
你可以设置为高亮状态
you can set this for the highlighted state,
或选择状态 或禁用状态
or the selected state, or disabled state.
我们将选择按钮的正常或默认状态
We’re just going to do the normal or default state of this button.
我们在设置这个按钮的背景图像
So we’re setting the background image for this button.
我们还需要设置标题 因为我们不希望
And we also need to set the title because we don’t want
翻过来后还能看到梅花 A
to see that ace of clubs when we flip it over backwards.
我将把它设为这个
So I’m just going to set it to that.
这是空字符串 这里我也可以用 nil
Okay. That’s the empty string. I could also say nil there.
不过我这里要写空字符串 让你们看看是怎样的
Okay. But I’m saying empty string just to see what empty string looks like.
我们可以运行这个
So actually if we run this,
Command 3
command three.
好 我试试
Okay, let’s try that.
哦 酷
Oh, cool.
好了
So there you go.
这是一个缩小的版本
So there’s a miniature version of it.
这是我们的纸牌
Okay. So here’s our card.
如果我点它一下
And if I click on it,
哦耶 它翻过来了
oh yeah, it flips over.
很好 带树的斯坦福 logo
Yes. Stanford logo with the tree.
但我再点它 它就不动了 永远是反面
But now if I click, it doesn’t do anything else; it always flips over to the back,
这正是我们代码的效果
which is exactly what our code does, right?
这很好
So that’s good.
我们来调整一下代码 让它能两面翻动
So let’s fix it so that it flips both ways.
我可以这样写 加上 if
And I’m going to do that by saying if the –
我还是先做另外一件事吧
actually, I’m going to do one other thing first
让代码更简单一些
to make this code a little simpler is instead
这里我可以不用这个局部变量
of having this local variable,
我可以直接把这些写到这里来
I can just take this and pop it right in there.
这是很常见的做法
And that’s very common to do that.
如果要换行 太长的话它会自动换行
And if I wanted to wrap it, it will automatically wrap if I make this too short.
不过我也可以键入一个回车
But I can also put a return in there.
这样做后 注意冒号的情况
And when I do, look what it does with the colons.
看到冒号对齐起来了吗
See how it lines the colons up?
它总会这样做
It will always do that.
如果你在多参数的信息发送中间敲了回车
If you press return in the middle of a message send that has multiple arguments,
它会为所有参数对齐冒号
it will line the colons up for all the arguments.
非常酷
Really cool.
这时所有参数都会像这样左右排列对齐
So you can see all the arguments lined up left and right.
无论如何 我将检验当前标题
So anyway, I’m going to check to see if the current title –
这是一个按钮方法
okay, that’s a button method –
如果它是字符串
if it’s a string.
如果这个长度不为 0
If that length, okay, is nonzero, okay –
这是用于检验长度是否不为 0
so that’s testing there to see if the length of nonzero –
这样做很酷 因为这会在
that’s a cool way to do it because that will work
按钮标题为 nil 或为空字符串时执行
if the button title is nil or if it’s the empty string.
因为按钮标题默认值是 nil
Because the button title starts out nil.
不设置为任何东西 最开始就是 nil
If you don’t set it to anything, it starts out nil.
这里通过一行代码 我同时检验了两种可能的初始状态
So here with one line of code I’ve checked both the initial state possibly –
这里不是如此 因为我们把标题设为了梅花 A
not in our case because we set the title to the A club –
不过你们的情况中 可能会是这样
but in your case it might be.
然后我们让它执行一段代码 否则执行另一段
Then we’ll set it to one thing, else we’ll set it to the other thing.
我们希望把这个设置到这里
So we just wanted to set this to this.
如果按钮上有标题
So if there’s a title on the button,
换言之 它上面有梅花 A 那我们就将翻到反面
in other words it has the ace of clubs, then we’re going to switch over to the back.
如果按钮上没有标题 那么我们就将翻回正面
And if there’s no title on the button, then we’re going to switch back to the front.
梅花 A
Ace of clubs.
之后我们如果运行 纸牌就能来回翻动了
So now when we run, our card will flip both ways.
将视图同控制器连接起来做你想做的事 其实很简单
So really simple to wire stuff into your controller to do what you want.
下面我们再来看这个
The next thing we’re going to do is in the –
这里我将快速展示一下
okay, I’ll show you really quickly here.
按住 Option 键 这个很重要的键
If you hold down the option key, a very important key,
看到它让光标变成问号 并开始高亮显示一些东西吗
do you see how it puts a question mark and starts highlighting things?
这让你能够转到说明文档
That’s going to allow to you to transition into the documentation.
如果关于这个 currentTitle 我想知道更多
So if I want to know more about this current title,
我可以 Option 点击它
if I hit option, click on it –
这里可以得到一些帮助
see, I get a little bit of help right here.
它是一种属性 它是只读的 非原子的
It’s a property. It’s read-only, it’s nonatomic.
记住 说明文档中凡是出现 retain 都表示 strong
By the way, if you see “retain” in the documentation, that’s the same as “strong.”
retain 其实说的也就是强
Retain is the same as strong basically.
这里有些描述 然后还有超链接
Little bit of description here but also hyperlinks.
如果我点击其中一个超链接 例如这个
And if I click on one of these hyperlinks, like this one,
我会进入说明文档
it takes me into the documentation.
这是一个单独打开的窗口
This is a separate window right here.
你可以在这个说明文档中进行浏览
And you can navigate around in this documentation.
所有这些你们都需要熟悉
You really want to get familiar with all this.
由于时间限制 我今天无法全部展示
I can’t really show it all to you today for time constraints,
不过你可以搜索 例如我可以搜索 UIButton
but you can do things like search, like I can go find UI button here.
这是 UIButton
Okay. There’s UI button.
我可以往下滚动到 例如
I might scroll down and go to, for example,
我们刚看到过的 setBackgroundImage:forState
set background image or set background image for state, which we just saw.
我还可以点击进入 UIImage
Maybe I’ll click to go UI image.
所有这些都在这里
You see all this.
一开始有对类的良好描述
There’s nice descriptions of the class in the beginning
然后所有方法 等等
and then all the methods, etc., etc.
你们必须掌握说明文档的使用方法
So definitely you want to become a master of that documentation.
你还可以 Option 双击
You can also option double-click on things
这会直接进入说明文档
and it will send you straight to the documentation.
不会给出小帮助提示 而是直接跳到说明文档
If you don’t want to get the little help one first, you can go straight in.
Option 是这里关键的键
So option is the key one for that.
然后再看
Let’s go ahead — okay.
下面这里有一些空白区域
Notice that this little space along the bottom here appeared
运行应用时 注意到了吗
when we ran the application — you see that?
左边这里是调试器 右边是控制台
This is the debugger on the left, and this is the console on the right.
课上你们肯定会用到调试器和控制台
And you are definitely going to be using the debugger and the console both in this class.
我也许没有时间演示控制台的用法
And actually, I might not have time to do a quick — show you how to do the console.
无论如何 你可以通过拖动将它隐藏起来
But anyway, you can hide it by dragging it down or also
或通过点击这个
by clicking this thing.
好 下面我们将要
All right. So the next thing we’re going to do is we’re going
在 UI 上加上一个记录数翻牌次数的小标签
to put a little label on our UI that counts the flips.
每次翻牌时 标签上的数字都会加一
A little incremental thing that increments every time there’s a flip.
要做这个 我们可以回到这里 抓取一个标签
And we do that by going back to here and grabbing ourselves a label.
标签是一段只读文本 不可编辑文本
So a label is a read-only piece of text, noneditable text.
我要把它拖放到左下角
And I’m just going to drag it over here and put it in the lower left.
双击它 改为 Flip: 0
I’m going to double-click on it to call it “flips colon zero.”
这是 UI 刚启动时我想要的效果
This is what I want it to look like when my UI first launches.
这个 我永远不会敲击它
Now here, I’m never going to be tapping on this
进而导致按钮那样的消息发送 它是反过来的
and causing a message to be sent like the button; it’s the other way around.
我的控制器希望同它通信 在翻牌进行时告诉它
My controller wants to talk to this and tell it when the flips changes all the time.
也许你会认为可以从代码拖到这个标签
So you might think that you would drag from your code down to this flips,
很不幸的是 你不能这样
but unfortunately you don’t do that.
你还是按住 Control 从这里开始拖动
You still hold down control and drag from here.
但不是拖到实现区
But instead of dragging it down into your implementation area,
而是拖到接口区
you drag it into the interface area
因为你要创建一个同该标签连接的属性
because you’re going to create a property that connects to that label basically.
我们这样做后得到这个
So we do that. We get a thing here.
问的问题略有不同
It’s asking us a little bit different questions:
属性名是什么
”What’s the name of this property?”
我将称其为 flipsLabel(翻牌标签)
I’m going to call it “flips label.”
注意到 该属性是弱的
Notice that this property is weak.
我点击连接时 它会创建一个弱属性
When I click connect, it’s going to make a property here and it’s going to be weak.
这是我们首次用弱代替强
This is the first time we’ve seen weak versus strong.
选弱的原因在于
The reason this is weak is because
该标签由视图本身很强地保持着
this label is held strongly by the view itself.
所以我们不需要用强指针指着它 来保证它在堆中
So we don’t need to have a strong pointer to it, to keep it in the heap.
视图会做这个
The view will.
如果该标签离开视图 它就会被清除出堆
And if this label ever leaves the view, it will get cleaned out from the heap.
而这个属性 这个指着它的指针
And this property — this pointer to it –
就会被设为 nil 这正是我们想要的
will get set to nil, which is exactly what we want.
因为当 flipsLabel 不在视图中时
Because if that flips label’s not in the view, we don’t want
我们就不想再更新和发消息给它了
to be updating it and sending messages to it.
所以说 这里对弱的使用很精妙
So it’s a great use of weak right here.
这里是你们很熟悉的通常属性 也许除了 IBOutlet
This is normal property that you’re used to except for maybe this IB outlet.
这同 IBAction 类似
That’s just like IB action.
这是无意义的 编译器会忽略 Xcode 使用它
It’s a meaningless thing the compiler ignores that Xcode is using.
这是用来做这个的
So that it can do this –
在鼠标悬停时显示连接到什么
show you what it’s connected to when you mouse over it.
你还可以通过右键点击来看所有连接
By the way, you can see all the connections by also right-clicking on things.
这里我右键点击了按钮 你可以看到它的连接
So here I just right-clicked on the button and you can see its connections.
如果你想重命名
If you ever want to rename –
例如我不喜欢 touchCardButton 我想重命名
like if I don’t like touch card button, I want to rename it to something,
很不幸 你不能重命名
you can’t just rename unfortunately.
你需要到这里 右键 使用这个小东西来断开连接
You have to go in here, right-click, use this little thing to disconnect it,
然后重新 Control 拖动
and then control drag again.
大家都明白了吗
Everybody got that?
很不幸
It’s unfortunate.
如果 Xcode 能跟踪这个就好了 可惜它不能
It would be really nice if Xcode could track that for you but it can’t.
所以 如果你想重命名什么东西
So if you ever want to rename something,
你需要通过右键点击来断开连接
you have to disconnect it here by right-clicking on it,
然后 Control 拖动一个新的 这样来设置名称
and then control drag a new one and set the name that way.
你还可以右键点击这个
You can also right-click on this little guy
这会显示出控制器的所有连接
and it will show you all the connections for your controller.
展开这个窗口
Brings up this window.
我可以看到标签
And I can see the label. You see?
鼠标现在在按钮上
I’m mousing over the button.
标签
Label.
这里还有一个属性 你们没有见过这个
There’s also this little property here, which is something you haven’t seen,
这是从控制器指向整个视图的属性
which is basically a property that points to the entire view from your controller.
这是到控制器的连接
So this is the connections to your controllers.
看到了吗 这里显示有纸牌游戏视图控制器
See, it says “card game view controller”?
这是右键点击
So that’s right-clicking.
我右键点击了这里
I’m right-clicking over here.
我们怎么让这个 flipsLabel 工作呢
So how are we going to make this flips label work?
我们先把它放一放
We are going to put it aside for a second.
先不想它
Let’s not think about it.
先来看另一个属性
Let’s instead do another property.
属性 它是非原子的
Property. Which is nonatomic,
它只是一个 int 型整数
which is just going to be an int,
命名为 flipCount(翻牌计数)
which I’m going to call “flip count.”
flipCount 是一个整数 用于记录翻牌次数
So flip count is just an integer that’s going to keep the count of flips.
再看这个
And watch this.
这里需要更多空间
Some more space here.
过来一些
Go there.
这里我只需要写 self.flipCount++
I’m just going to go down here and say self.flip count plus plus.
这调用的是 flipCount 的 setter 还是 getter
Now, does that call the setter or the getter for flip count?
两者都 对
Both. Exactly.
这同时调用了 setter 和 getter
That is calling both the setter and the getter.
调用 getter 来获得 flipCount
It’s calling the getter to get the flip count,
然后对它进行 ++
then it’s plus plussing it;
然后调用 setter 来设置值
and then it’s calling the setter to set it back.
这是一种很别致的代码写法
Okay. So that’s kind of a funky lining of code right there.
等价于 self.flipCount=self.flipCount+1
That’s the same as saying self.flip count equals self.flip count plus one.
它会调用 getter 和 setter
So it’s calling the getter and the setter.
好 现在我们有了这个很好的 flipCount
Okay. So now we’ve got this nice flip count.
它记录计数值 如何将它同这个联系起来呢
It’s keeping track of the count; how do we hook that up to this thing over here?
这个我要弄大一些
Which I’m going to make a little bigger, by the way.
如何同这个联系起来 让它改写为 Flips: 1
Okay. How do we hook that up so that says flips colon one,
Flips: 2 及 Flips: 3 这些
flips colon two, flips colon three?
我们将使用 flipCount 的 setter 来做到这个
Well, we’re going to do it using the setter for flip count.
普通情况下 flipCount 的 setter 是这样的
So normally a setter for flip count would look like this.
这是 setter 和 getter 的另一妙用
And here’s another great use of setters and getters,
也就是让 UI 同属性保持同步
which is to keep UI in sync with a property.
这里我要写 self.flipsLabel.text =…
And I’ll just do this by saying self.flips label.text equals –
哦 抱歉 站着打字很不方便
oops, sorry. It’s hard to type standing up.
= NSString stringWithFormat…
Equals NS string, string with format,
这个你们见过 Flips: %d
which you’ve seen before, flips colon percent D
self.flipCount
self.flip count.
这样 每次 flipCount 变动时 我们都会更新 UI
So now every time flip count is changed we’re going to update the UI.
能明白吗 这里有任何问题吗
Make sense? Any questions about that?
好 我们来运行
Okay. So let’s run.
好的 程序运行
Okay. Here’s our thing.
点击 翻面 翻牌计数更新了
So click, flips over, flip count updates.
翻 翻 翻 翻
Flip, flip, flip, flip.
来回都行 而 flipCount 正确记录着
Back and forth working, and the flip count is keeping track
翻了多少次
of how many flips we’re doing.
可以看到 这些很容易连接起来
So you can see this stuff is really simple to wire up.
在你开始创建更复杂的应用时
And, you know, when you get into building even complicated applications,
因为你总是在使用相同的目标动作和 outlet 机制
because you’re always going to use these same mechanisms
with target action and outlets
而且你将使用 setter 和 getter 来保持事物同步
and you’re going to be using setters and getters to keep things in sync,
这会让人们更容易理解你的代码如何工作
it’s going to be easy for people to understand how your code works.
他们知道在哪去看的 UI 更新发生
They know where to look to see where UI updating happens,
等等 这里我还要做一件事
etc. I’m going to do one other thing here.
花点时间展示 NSLog
Take a minute and show you NS log.
我说过 你可以在控制台中记录日志
Okay. I told you that you could log something in the console.
这里每次有变化时 让我们都用 NSLog 进行记录
So let’s do every time this thing changes, let’s do an NS log.
这只是一个 C 函数
So it’s just a C function.
像 printf 一样给它一个格式字符串
And you give it a format string like printf.
这里我用 flipCount = %d
So I’ll say flip count equals percent d
self.flipCount
self.flip count.
这就加入了这个 NSLog
So you just put that NS log in there,
于是运行时 你就会在控制台看到它
and now when we run you’re going to see it in the console.
我点击时 它会出现在这里 显示发生了什么
It’s going to come up when I click, and it’s going to say what happened here.
当然 我也可以把它拉宽一些
By the way, of course, I can make that wider.
回到模拟器 看
And go back to the simulator. Let’s see.
NSLog 是一种很棒的调试方式
So NS logging — awesome way to debug.
有时比设置断点要容易很多
Sometimes a lot easier than setting a breakpoint
这里会给你打印出来
and then when you get there looking at the variables and stuff.
你可以随时观察
It just prints out what’s going on and you can watch it.
特别是在 UI 中 有时会是动画 它们随时间发生
Especially in the UI things are sometimes animated, they’re happening over time.
在动画中间设置断点会很困难
It’s sometimes hard to set a breakpoint in the middle
of an animation to see what’s going on.
但使用 NSLog 你就能看到程序是怎么在运行了
but if you do some NS logs, you can kind of see how things progress.
我要展示的最后一点内容是 如何为 app 添加一个新类
The last thing I’m going to show you here is how to add a new class to your app
因为你们到时要在这个基础上自行添加四个类
because you’re going to need to do that. You’re going to add four classes to this.
你们将从这个开始
You’re going to start with this, okay,
然后添加四个类
and then you’re going to add four classes –
Card Deck 等等
card, deck, etc.
添加一个类的做法如下
And the way you add a class is you –
实际上 往项目中添加任何文件的方式都是这样
and in fact, the way you add any file to your project –
也就是到文件菜单 点选新 文件
is you go to the file menu, new file.
这里你可以添加各种东西
And there’s all different kinds of things you can add here,
数据库文件 架构文件等等
database file, schema files and everything.
不过你所需要的是左上角这个 Objective-C 类
But you want this one top-left Objective-C class.
这里你要键入类名
Here you’re just going to type the name of the class.
例如 这里我要添加的是 Card 然后是父类名
So for example, if I’m going to add card and the name of the superclass.
如果是 PlayingCard 这里可以键入 Card
Okay. If you are doing playing card, you can type card here.
并不一定要从这个列表中选择 iOS 默认的
It doesn’t have to be something that’s chosen from this list, which are the iOS ones.
这里我要创建的是 Card
So here I’m going to make card.
我可以把 Card 放到这里
I could put card right here.
它问我在哪存储这个
It’s asking where to store this.
我可以放到同纸牌游戏控制器相同的位置
I could put it right in the same place that my card game controller is, you see?
但我不大推崇
But I’m actually a big fan
将模型放到它自身的目录下
of putting your model in its own directory.
我希望你们使用新文件夹
So you would use new folder down here.
例如可以创建一个 Model 目录
Let’s create like a model directory,
于是这里有了一个 Model 目录
and that creates a model directory here.
这是控制器 这是模型目录
There’s a controller, here’s the model directory.
创建
And so create.
这会创建 Card.h 和.m
So that’s going to create card dot H and M.
这是 Card.h 和.m 目前还是空白
Here’s card dot H and M, okay, kind of blank versions of them.
你可以在它们之间来回切换
You can switch back and forth between them here.
注意到 如果我改变左边 右边会随之变化
Notice that if I switch the left, the right changes to match.
看到了吗 改变这个 这个随之变化
You see? Change this, this matches.
这是因为这里我选了 counterparts(对应)
That’s because I have counterparts chosen right here.
如果使用 manual 手动设置这个
If you go to manual and pick this file manually,
这时它就不会这样做了
then it won’t be doing that magic anymore.
不过你总是可以选回 counterparts 这会保持同步
But you can always go back to counterparts and it will keep them in sync.
有些人喜欢让头文件在左
Okay. So you can have — some people like their header file on the left,
有些人则喜欢在右
some on the right, whatever.
还要注意到这里
Also, notice over here
这些在导航栏中能够组起来 这很棒
it would be nice if I can also group these things in the navigator.
我只需要选择它们 右键点击 新组
And I can by having them selected right-click new group.
命名为 Model
Say model.
这样我就将我的模型放到了这个小地方
Right here. And now I’ve put my model in its own little place right here.
我可以将它移动到下面这里 诸如此类
I can even move this around, put it down here, whatever.
我可以把所有四个类都放到这里
I could put all my four classes in there.
还可以将这个组同文件系统连起来
It is possible to link this group to the file system.
实际上 你可以点击文件 在这里打开检查器
In fact, if you just click on a file and bring up the inspector on it right here,
可以看到有这些可供选择
you can see that it’s got this location
你可以指定是绝对路径
where you can specify whether it’s an absolute path,
还是相对于它所在的组 等等
or relevant to the group it’s in, or whatever.
这是可以控制的
So you can control that.
就这些了
And that’s it.
知道这些就能开始做作业了
So I think that’s all you need to do your homework.
你们需要键入 Card 的所有代码 并加入另三个类
You’re just going to type in all your code here for card and add your three other ones.
键入所有代码
Type all that code in.
你们要让纸牌不是总显示梅花 A
And then all you got to do is make that card instead of showing ace of clubs all the time,
你需要在牌堆中抽取
needs to go through the deck.
我发布有详细的作业指南
There’s a detailed homework write up posted.
其中有各种提示和帮助 告诉你需要做哪些任务
It has all kinds of hints and help, and tells you about what the required tasks are,
还有评定标准 等等所有这些
and evaluation criteria, and all that stuff.
所以请务必仔细阅读
So definitely read that thing in detail.
不要跳过 不要直接做作业
Don’t skip that stuff and just try to go straight to doing it.
有问题的 现在可以来提 下课
And if you have questions, I’ll be here. That’s it.
更多内容 请访问我校官网 stanford.edu
For more, please visit us at Stanford.edu.